<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Astrologie theologized: wherein is set forth, vvhat astrologie, and the light of nature is. What influence the starres naturally have on man, and how the same may be diverted and avoided. As also, that the outward man, how eminent soever in all naturall and politicall sciences, is to bee denied, and die in us. And, that the inward man by the light of grace, through profession and practice of a holy life, is to be acknowledged and live in us: which is the onely means to keep the true Sabbath in inward holinesse, and free from outward pollution. / By Valentine Weigelius.</title>
            <author>Weigel, Valentin, 1533-1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E562_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204068</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863776</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863776</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E562[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Astrologie theologized: wherein is set forth, vvhat astrologie, and the light of nature is. What influence the starres naturally have on man, and how the same may be diverted and avoided. As also, that the outward man, how eminent soever in all naturall and politicall sciences, is to bee denied, and die in us. And, that the inward man by the light of grace, through profession and practice of a holy life, is to be acknowledged and live in us: which is the onely means to keep the true Sabbath in inward holinesse, and free from outward pollution. / By Valentine Weigelius.</title>
                  <author>Weigel, Valentin, 1533-1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Whittington, at the blue Anchor in Cornhill, neer the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ASTROLOGIE Theologized: Wherein is ſet forth, VVhat <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> and the <hi>light of Nature</hi> is. What influence the Starres naturally have on Man, and how the ſame may be diverted and avoided.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, That the outward Man, how eminent ſoever in all Naturall and Politicall Sciences, is to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and die in us.</p>
            <p>AND, That the Inward man by the <hi>light of Grace,</hi> through profeſſion and practice of a holy life, is to be acknowledged and live in us: Which is the onely means to keep the true Sabbath in inward holineſſe, and free from outward pollution.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Valentine Weigelius.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sapiens dominabitur Astris.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Whittington,</hi> at the blue Anchor in Cornhill, neer the Royall Exchange. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165235:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165235:2"/>
            <head>Aſtrologie Theologized.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is, and what <hi>Theologie;</hi> and how they have reference one to another.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Strologie</hi> is Philoſophie it ſelf,<note place="margin">The Kingdom of Nature.</note> or it is the whole <hi>light of Nature,</hi> from whence ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the univerſall naturall Wiſdome, or a ſolid, ſincere, and exquiſite knowledge of naturall things: which light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is twofold, externall, and internall: Externall in the Macrocoſm, internall in the Microcoſm. Or, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knowledge of good and evill, which is, and bears rule in things ſubject to Nature; which ſcience flouriſhing in man, unleſſe it be ruled and governed by <hi>Theologie,</hi> that is, divine Wiſdome, as the handmaid by her miſtreſſe, it is vicious. And by her ſpecious appearance, and concupiſcible jucundity man ſeduceth himſelf, and as it were by eating of the forbidden tree, or by who reing with the creatures, he maketh his ſoule the Babylonian Whore ſitting upon the Beaſt, having ſeven heads and ten hornes, &amp;c. and being ſweetly deceived of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, obtains eternall death to himſelf.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Theologie</hi> is the whole <hi>light of grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Kingdom of grace.</note> happening to man from the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> effuſed from above, which is the univerſall wiſdome of the Kingdom of Heaven, and the ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165235:3"/>of divine and ſupernaturall things, making chaſt and purging the ſoul from every defilement of ſin abiding in the mortall body; in reſpect whereof that naturall Wiſdome is but a ſhadow, which, when the world is blotted out and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, will together with it be blotted out and removed, and then Theologie alone ſhall reigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is ſo called becauſe it ariſeth from the Stars. As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theologie,</hi> becauſe it flowes from God.</p>
               <p>To live <hi>Astrologically</hi> is with a pleaſing concupiſence to eat of the Tree of the knowledge of good and evill, and to bring death to himſelf.</p>
               <p>To live <hi>Theologically</hi> is, to eat of the wood and Tree of life by an intimate abnegation of ones ſelf, and thence to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ones ſelf, Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Light of Nature</hi> in <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> with his incitative fruits, is the probatory inſtrument whereby Man placed in the midſt, that is, between God and the Creature is proved which way he would direct or convert his free will, deſire, love and appetite; whether to God his Creatour, by loving him above all things, with his whole heart, with his whole mind, with his whole ſoul, and with his whole ſtrength; which ſhould be the <hi>Theologicall</hi> life. Or whether caſting God behind, he would reflect to himſelf and to the Creature by love of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and arrogating of good things received, which was the Aſtrologicall life, at the Babiloniſh fornication, as will appear by that which followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> poſſeſſeth our ſoul with the externall body, wherein the Light of Nature dwells and ſhines forth, in ſome more excellently, in others leſſe. And it contains in it ſelf two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All kind of Sciences, Arts, Tongues, Faculties and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Studies; all the gifts, as well of the mind, as of the body, and alſo all negotiations, occupations, actions and labours of men, how many ſoever of them are found, exerciſed and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in all times upon the whoſe earth, every where amongſt men, aſwell groſſe as ſubtile, aſwell old as new, ſerving aſwell to good as to bad uſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Under <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> are referred all orders, ſtates and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165235:3"/>of men, diſtinctions of perſons, dignities, gifts, offices, and every kind of life as well naturally ordained by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as thought of and invented by humane wit, and found out in the whole world from the higheſt and moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the loweſt and moſt baſe.</p>
               <p>All theſe are the fruits of the Starrs, and have their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall from <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> and pertain to the body and ſoul, and may be as well good as bad, according to the divers pleaſures of the uſers and abuſers.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Theologie</hi> poſſeſſeth our Spirit which we have from God, which alone is <hi>Theologus,</hi> that is the Speech of God, the Breath of God, the Word of God, being and inhabiting in the Temple of our heart, from which alone according to ſacred Letters true <hi>Theologie</hi> is to be drawn forth; That is, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, of things divine and celeſtiall and ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ariſing from within, from the illumination of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit it ſelf dwelling within us: According to whoſe beck, will and command we ought to inſtitute, direct and finiſh all our Sciences, Arts, Studies, Actions, Offices, Vocations, Induſtries, Labors and kinds of of life, invented &amp; drawn forth on earth from the Light of Nature; ſo as whatſoever we think, ſay or do in the world, in all Arts, Sciences and Labors, it all proceeds from the Will of God, and ſeems as it were to be done and governed by God himſelf in us, as by his fit inſtruments.</p>
               <p>For every Aſtrologicall gift comming from the Light of <hi>Nature,</hi> ought to be ruled and ſubjected to the Divine will by the Theologicall Spirit dwelling in us, that ſo the will of the Lord be done, <hi>as in heaven, ſo alſo in earth.</hi> For all Wiſdome both Naturall and Supernaturall is from the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is the ſcience of tilling and perluſtrating of the inferiour terreſtiall earth, ground, garden, Paradiſe, from which Man was taken and made, as to his body and his ſoul, in the labor and culture whereof ſix daies were ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: But becauſe this Science of it ſelf confers not Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and eternall Beatitude, but alone belongs to this preſent life: it is neceſſary the Lady and Miſtreſſe of all Sciences and Arts, <hi>Theologie,</hi> be added, which ſeeing it is Wiſdome from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, it hath in it ſelf the Science of tilling and perluſtrating
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165235:4"/>the celeſtiall earth, ground, garden, paradiſe, from whence alſo man was taken, created according to the ſimilitude and image of God, which garden man alſo hath in himſelf, to the culture whereof, the ſeventh day alone, which is the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, is appointed.</p>
               <p>For ſo it was ordained <hi>between God and man from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that Man ſhould be God, and God Man, neither without the other: that is, as God himſelf is, and will be the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, Garden, Tabernacle, Manſion, Houſe, Temple, and Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem of Man: So alſo was man created for the ſame end, that he ſhould be the Paradiſe, Garden, Tabernacle, Manſion, Houſe, Temple, and Jeruſalem of God: that by this mutuall union and friendſhip of God with Man, and of Man with God, all the wiſdome, power, vertue and glory eternally hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in God, ſhould be opened and multiplied. For, God once made all things for man, but Man for himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Concerning the ſubject of Aſtrologie.</head>
               <p>THe ſtudy of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> or Philoſophie is converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the univerſall knowledge of all the wonderfull and ſecret things of God, infuſed and put into naturall things from above in the firſt creation.</p>
               <p>The exerciſe therefore of the light of Nature is the moſt ſagacious perſcrutation and enucleation of the abſtruſe, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and inviſible vertues, lying hid in externall, corporall and viſible things; to wit,</p>
               <p>What ſhould be the firſt matter of this great world where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it was made.</p>
               <p>What the Elements ſhould be, and thoſe things which are bred of the Elements, and conſiſt in them; of what kind is their creation, eſſence, nature, propriety and operation as well within as without.</p>
               <p>What might be in the Stars of Heaven, what their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>What in Volatiles, what in Fiſhes, Metalls, Mineralls,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165235:4"/>Gemms; what in every ſpecies of Sprigs and Vegetables.</p>
               <p>What in Animalls, beaſts, creeping things, and in the whole frame of the world.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, what is in Man, who was made and created of all theſe; to wit,</p>
               <p>What is that maſſe, or ſlime, or duſt whereof the body of the firſt man was formed, and whence he received his ſoule, and what it is: and whence he hath the Spirit, and what he is: And ſo the light of Nature, or <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> comprehends in it ſelf all the wiſdome and knowledge of the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; that is, all theſe are had and learned in the Schoole of the light of Nature, and are referred to <hi>Astrologie,</hi> or are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> it ſelf: to wit,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſubject of Astrologie</hi> therefore is double; the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm and Microcoſm, the greater World, and the leſſer World.</p>
               <p>The <hi>greater World</hi> is this very frame and great houſe, or this huge tabernacle wherein we inhabit and live; and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of the foure Elements, Fire, Aire, Water and Earth; and is twofold, viſible according to the body, inviſible, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſoule or ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The leſſer World</hi> is Man, the off-ſpring, or ſome of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter world, extracted and compoſed out of the whole greater World, who alſo in himſelf is two fold, viſible and externall, as to his body, inviſible and internall, as to his ſoul.</p>
               <p>And as Man is made of nothing els but the world, ſo alſo is he placed and put no where els but within the world, to wit, that he might live, dwell, and walk therein, yet ſo as that he ſhould take heed of that ſubtill Serpent, and ſhould not eat of the Tree of the knowledge of good and evill, leaſt he die; that is, that he ſerve not the ſoule of the world, and creatures ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to vanity: but as a wiſe man rule the Starrs, and reſiſt the divell tempting him, by the concupiſcence of the fleſh, of the eyes and pride of life; and ſuppreſſe ſinfull nature, living and walking in wiſdom and ſimplicity of the Divine God head in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired into him, not in the ſubtilty of the Serpent by arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and love of himſelfe. For it is moſt certain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of what any thing is born and procreated, from thence alſo it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165235:5"/>ſeeks, deſires and receives it's nouriſhments, convenient to it's eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and nature for the ſuſtentation of it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Man was taken from, and compoſed of the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, and placed in the ſame: Therefore alſo neceſſarily he is nouriſhed, cheriſhed, receives his meat and drink, is clothed and ſuſtained according to that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. v. 19. <hi>Thou art taken from the earth, and thou ſhalt eat thereof in labour all the dayes of thy life, and ſhalt eat the herbes of the field untill thou ſhalt return unto the earth, for from it thou art taken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing therefore Man, as to his body, is compoſed of the Elements, and as to his ſoul, of the Starrs, and each part is fed and ſuſtained from that from which it was taken: The food or aliment of the body, wherby the body grows to a due ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, comes to a man from the Elements, the Earth, the Water, Ayre, &amp; Fire; not that Man ſhould take to himſelf for food the crude bodies of the Elements, but the fruit growing from the Elements: they are for nutriment. But the food of the ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting in the Microcoſmicall body, are all kinds of Sciences, Arts, Faculties, and Induſtries, with which ſhe tincts and makes her ſelf perfect.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>All aliment paſſeth into the ſubſtance of the uſer, and is made the ſame that he himſelf is;</hi> that is, whatſoever a man eats, and drinks, the ſame thing is eſſentially tranſmitted into the ſubſtance, nature, propriety and forme of Man, by the digeſtion of Arthens in the ventricle. I ſay, the food paſſeth and is converted into the nature of the eater, and drink into the ſubſtance of the drinker, and is made one and the ſame with him.</p>
               <p>And in the firſt place, let theſe things be underſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the body without wonder: becauſe man is made of that which he eats and drinks.</p>
               <p>So alſo whatſoever a man learns, ſtudies, knowes in things that are placed without himſelf, that knowledge and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence paſſeth into the very eſſence, nature and propriety of a man, and is made one with him.</p>
               <p>The Light of Nature is made Man in Man, and by a mans di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearching, Man is made Light both in light and by light; and by the benefit of that light he finds out all things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165235:5"/>he ſeeks and deſires: but one more and another leſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all do not ſeek with the like ſtudy.</p>
               <p>Every Knowledge, Science, Art, Induſtry and Faculty paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth into the nature of Man, penetrates him, occupies him, poſſeſſeth him, tincts him, is agglutinated to him, united with him, and perfected in him, and he in it. For, <hi>Whatſoever kind of aliment man uſeth, and whatſoever he endeavours to ſtudy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, know, and underſtand, this is not ſtrange or different from his eſſence and nature.</hi> The reaſon is,</p>
               <p>Becauſe whatſoever is without a man, the ſame is alſo within him, for that man is made of all thoſe things which are without him, that is of the whole univerſe of things.</p>
               <p>Therefore whatſoever Man takes from without from the Elements and Stars by meat, drink, knowledge, ſtudy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, this is the ſame that man is, and is made the ſame with Man: So man eating bread, and drinking water, wine, &amp;c. from the Macrocoſme, he eats and drinks himſelf; and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Arts, Tongues, Faculties, and Sciences of externall things, he learns and knows himſelf.</p>
               <p>And as he tincts his body by meat and drink, which paſſe into the ſubſtance of fleſh and blood, ſo alſo his ſoul is tincted with whatſoever kind of Sciences, Arts, &amp;c. eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king he is united eſſentially with that which he eats and drinks: And learning and knowing he is united eſſentially with that which he ſtudies, learns and knows: Wherefore this is a moſt certain rule,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whatſoever is without us, is alſo within us.</hi> Which in this place, we, philoſophiſing of the ſoul and the body, do thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</p>
               <p>This whole world viſible, as to the body, inviſible as to it's ſoul, is without us. From this we are all eſſentially in and with the firſt man complicitly made and created, and incontinently after the Creation were put and placed into it. And ſeeing it is manifeſt,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That every thing that is derived retaines the eſſence, nature and propriety of it's originall:</hi> That although the Macrocoſme is without us, yet nevertheleſſe it may alſo be found truly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:165235:6"/>
               <p>I ſay the World is in us, and we are in it, and yet this is, as that is without us, and we without that. For indeed we have no exiſtence or originall from any thing els, but from that which is without us, and which was before us: Nor are we, nor do wee inhabit, walk and live in any thing els, ſave in that weherof we are made. Neither do we ſeek and draw forth meat and drink from any other, either for the body or the ſonl, but from that into which we are placed, and which is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in us.</p>
               <p>As to the Spirit, we are of God, move in God, and live in God, and are nouriſhed of God: Hence God is in us and we are in God: God hath put and placed himſelf in us, and we are put and placed in God.</p>
               <p>As to the Soul, we are from the Firmament and Starrs, we wove and live therein, and are nouriſhed thereof: Hence the Firmanment with it's aſtralick vertues and operations is in us, and we in it. The Firmament is put and placed in us, and we are put and placed in the Firmament.</p>
               <p>As to the Body, we are of the Elements, we move and live in them, and are nouriſhed of them: Hence the Elements are in us and we in them. The Elements by the ſlime are put and placed in us, and we are put and placed in them.</p>
               <p>So God is whole without us. and alſo whole within us, by the being of inſpiration, that is, by his ſpirit communicated to us.</p>
               <p>So the World is whole without <hi>Adam,</hi> and alſo the whole World is within <hi>Adam,</hi> by the <hi>being of extracted ſlyme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Adam</hi> is whole without us, and alſo whole within us, by the <hi>being of ſeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we bear God within us, and God bears us in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. God hath us with himſelf, and is neerer to us, then we are to our ſelves. We have God every where with us, whether we know it, or know it not.</p>
               <p>We bear the World in us, and the World bears us in it ſelf. Therefore whatſoever we perceive, feel, touch, taſt, ſmell, hear, ſee, imagine, think, ſpeculate, learn, underſtand, ſavour, know, eat, and drink, and whereſoever we walk, this the very ſame from whence we have drawn our originall. We are alwaies
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165235:6"/>converſant in thoſe things of which we are made. For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Man is the centre of the whole univerſe.</hi> So we learn nothing els, but the very ſame thing that was before us, and whereof we are made, and which before we begin to learn, lies hid in us. Yea, we learn, ſearch, and know nothing els then our <hi>ſelves:</hi> to wit, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſearching and knowing that whereof we come, and whence we have received our being. So we eat and drink nothing els but our ſelves, to wit, eating and drinking that whereof we are made.</p>
               <p>So our body hath it's hunger and thirſt in it ſelf from within, and deſires perfection of it ſelf by meat and drink taken fromthe Elements from without.<note place="margin">See <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus</hi> of the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of Nature in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So the ſoul hath it's hunger and thirſt in it ſelf, and deſires the perfection of it ſelf, by meat and drink from the Starrs, which is the wiſdom and knowledge of naturall things; by Arts, Tongues, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, &amp;c. Hence ſpring the Artificers and Wiſemen of this world.</p>
               <p>Moreover, as in meat and drink taken from the Elements, there is alwaies pure and impure conjoyned, which when they come into the ſtomach to the Fire of digeſtion, are by the internall Vulcan or Arthens of Nature ſeparated from one another after a ſpagiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call manner, an that which is pure is retained and abides in us, that is the eſſence extracted from meat and drink, the pure is ſeparated from the impure which paſſeth into fleſh and blood: For it pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates the body like unto leven, and is made one with it, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to incrtaſe, that it may become greater and more ſolid in it's ſtrength and nerves: but the impure differing from nutriment is caſt forth into the draught, and that by the operation of Arthens labouring in the ventricle. By like reaſon the matter is even in all Sciences ariſing from the Light of Nature, where alwaies good and evill are joyned together. For in Nature all things are convertible, as well to good as to evill. Wherefore unleſſe <hi>Astroiogie</hi> be <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logized,</hi> that is, unleſſe that which is good be retained, and that which is evill rejected, Man from thence acquires to himſelf eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death. And this the probation of Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:165235:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the three parts of man: Spirit Soule and Body, from whence every one is taken, and how one is in the other.</head>
               <p>THe parts of the Univerſe, of which the whole Man is made, are three; The World of Eternity, the Evial World; and the World of Time: The parts of Man are three, Spirit, Soul, and Body: and theſe three parts ſpring and are taken from theſe three parts of the whole Univerſe.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of Man comes from the Spirit of God, and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates with Eternity and <hi>Aevo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soul in Man is extracted from the ſoul of the world, and participates with <hi>Aevo</hi> and Time.</p>
               <p>The Body of Man is formed and compoſed from the body of the world, as Elements, and participates with Time only.</p>
               <p>The Body extracted from the Elements, and conſtituted into this form, is the Houſe, the Tabernacle, the ſeat of the Soul, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident chiefly in the heart.</p>
               <p>The Soul of Man extracted from the ſoul of the world, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over to the heart, is the habitation of the Divine Spirit, and hath the Divine Spirit in it ſelf.</p>
               <p>So one exiſts inthe other, and dwells in the other, abides in the other, and operates in the other.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Spirit in the Soul, and by the Soul.</item>
                  <item>The Soul in the Body, and by the Body.</item>
                  <item>The Body in and by externall ſubjects.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every thing which is without is as that which is within,</hi> but the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall alwaies excels the externall in eſſence, vertue &amp; operation. For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By how much any thing is more inward, by ſo much the more it is more noble, potent and capacious.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Great vertue is in the Body, if it be excited.</item>
                  <item>Greater in the Soul of the Firmament, if it be excited.</item>
                  <item>Greateſt in the Divine Spirit, if it be exhited.</item>
               </list>
               <p>By excitation all things are laid open, which are hidden and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Ignorance. For both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Naturall</hi> Wiſdom ſleep in us, and each light ſhines in darkneſſe, and without excitation Man wants the having.</p>
               <p>Great and excellent is the knowledgeof the humane body, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the Elements and diſpoſed into this form.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:165235:7"/>
               <p>Greater and more excellent is the knowledge of the Soul, taken from the Firmament, and inſerted into the body.</p>
               <p>Greateſt and moſt excellent is the knowledge of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired from the mouth of God into the firſt man, and by the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of multiplication equally communicated to every one of us.</p>
               <p>Wherefore is <hi>the knowledge of the humane body great?</hi> By reaſon of it's wonderfull compoſition, that is, becauſe all the foure Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are eſſentially compoſed in it. And moreover I ſay, the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nature &amp; propriety of all the creatures of the whole <hi>inviſible world</hi> which are in the Earth, Water, Air, and Fire, are incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſcituate in Man: But ſeeing all things generally are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and included into one skin, they are not altogether and at once diſcovered, nor can be revealed, but at leaſt come forth and are known <hi>inſpecie,</hi> as they are drawn forth and excited.</p>
               <p>Wherefore is <hi>the knowledge of the Soul which is in the heart of Man greater?</hi> Becauſe the whole Firmament, with all the eſſence, nature, vertue, propriety, inclination, operation and effect of all the Starrs is therein conjoyned and complicated, ſo as there is nothing in the whole power of the Spirit of the Firmament or ſoul of the world, which the ſoul of man alſo hath not in himſelf, and in the exaltation of it ſelf, can give it of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Yea, the whole Light of Nature is in the ſoul of the Microcoſm, which is the wiſdome and power and vigour of all things of the whole whorld throughout all the Elements and things procreated of the Elements. For ſhe is the Aſtrologicall Spirit containing in her ſelf all kind of Sciences, Magic, Cabaliſtic, Aſtronomic with all their Species, Chimiſtry, Medicine, Pahiſic, all Arts, Tongues, all Workmanſhips and all Studies exiſtent throughout the whole ſhop of Nature.</p>
               <p>But becauſe all theſe things are collected in one, and generally comprehended in the ſoul, they do not all lie open or can they be in act to gether, although they are in power; but are let out and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced one ſpecies after an other.</p>
               <p>Whereſoever therefore theſe kinds of divers Sciences flouriſh &amp; are exerciſed amongſt men, there ſhines the Light of Nature, and the ſoul of the Microcoſme is in her exaltation, that is the Firmament of the Microcoſme is in his aſcendents.</p>
               <p>But <hi>why is the knowledge of the Spirit of God greateſt in us?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he from whom we receive this Spirit is greateſt and moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165235:8"/>above all. For in this ſame Spriit all the <hi>divine Wiſdome</hi> and Power from whence that ſaving knowledge flowes forth, that is, Theologie, treating of ſupernaturall celeſtiall and divine things, and is converſant in the <hi>Magnalia</hi> and myſteries of <hi>God</hi> placed above Nature, and tends even to the <hi>inexhauſted and unſpeakable profundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Deity, in which profundity,</hi> the very origianll matter, cauſe &amp; end of al the works of God, and of things acted in time from the beginning of the Creation even to the end of the conſummation of the world, eternally and eſſentially lay hid. For all things came forth from him; all things were made by him, and all things conſiſt in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By how much any thing is moſt inward, by ſo much it is more noble and excellent.</hi> This viſible world is a body compacted of Fire, Air, Water, and Earth, which is without, hath in it ſelf the Spirit of Nature which is the ſoul of the world which is within; to which ſoul this externall body be longeth: becauſe it is inhabited, poſſeſſed and governed by it. Hence the ſoul of the world is more noble then the body.</p>
               <p>This ſoul of the world hath in it the Spirit of God, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth and poſſeſſeth it. For nothing is beyond God or the Spirit of God. Hence the Spirit is more noble then the Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The more noble alwaies exiſts in the more ignoble, and internalls prevail over externells, as well in eſſence as in power.</hi> So our externall body is indeed great in it's ſtature and quantity, and a wonderfull creature.</p>
               <p>Yet the ſoul dwelling in the body is far greater, and more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, not in corporeall quantity, but in Eſſence, Vertue and Power.</p>
               <p>But the Spirit is the greateſt of all, not in the lump or corporeall quantity, but in Eſſence, Vertue, and Power; and therefore moſt wonderfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is nothing greater then that in which are all things.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is nothing leſſe then that which is in all ſmalleſt things.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us obſerve this rule well:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By how much any thing is more inward and more hidden from the externall ſenſes, by ſo much the more it is more worthy, noble and potent in it's eſſence, nature and propriety.</hi> Which we will demonſtrate by exanples.</p>
               <p>There is not any houſe built for it ſelf, but for the inhabitant.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165235:8"/>Now the edifice is an externall thing, and the inhabitant and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thing. The houſe is for the gueſt, and not the gueſt for the houſe. Therefore the inhabitant is far more noble, worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celllent in his eſſence then every edifice, although ſumptuous. For, what is the houſe profitable, the gueſt being abſent?</p>
               <p>So garments are made and prepared for the body, that it might be and walk in them. Garments are externall things: the body is internall. Therefore the body in its eſſence is far more noble and worthy then all garments, although precious. For, what need is there of garments, if they are wanting which ſhould put them on? Therefore garments are for the body, and not the body for gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>So the Body, rayment, houſe and habitation is a certain exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thing to the ſoul, but the ſoul is internall.</p>
               <p>And the body is for the ſoul, and not the ſoul for the body. Therefore the ſoul in her eſſence is a far more noble and worthy Creature then the body, although moſt comely and moſt excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proportioned. For, what availeth the body, the ſoule being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it is a carcaſſe.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Soul,</hi> made and created for an habitation of the Divine Spirit, is externall: but the <hi>Spirit</hi> is internall. And the ſoul is for the Spirit, and not the Spirit for the ſoul. Therefore the Spirit of God is found far more noble and excellent, and worthy in his ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall eſſence, nature, vertue, power and propriety.</p>
               <p>So God is and abides the moſt inward, chief, great, potent, noble and worthy above all things: adn contains all things in himſelf, and he himſelf is contained of none. Moreover,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By how much any thing is more inward, by ſo much it is more nigh and neer to us, but alſo ſo much the harder to be found and known.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Every thing that is moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and moſt noble.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe of the too much averſion and abalienation of our ſoul from divine and heavenly things: and by reaſon of the too much tenacity and adherency of our love to the Creatures of the world. And on the contrary,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By how much any thing is more exterior, by ſo much the more it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from us, and by ſo much the more ſtrange.</hi> For example ſake,</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spirit of the Lord</hi> truly is and inhabiteth in my ſoul, whoſe ſeat is in the captula of my heart: But ſeeing every inhabitant is whthin and his habitation without, it followeth, That the Spirit of the Lord is more near to me then I am to my ſelf. And ſo it moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165235:9"/>appears, <hi>That the Kingdom of God is not to be ſought without us, here or there, but within us:</hi> witneſſe Chriſt himſelf, who ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. being asked of the Phariſes when the Kingdome of God ſhould come: The Kingdom of God ſhall not come with obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; neither ſhall they ſay, loe here, or loe there; For, <hi>Behold the Kingdom of God is within you.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> 14. <hi>Rom. The Kingdom of God is not meat and drink, but righteouſneſſe and peace, and joy in the holy Spirit.</hi> For by theſe he which doth ſervice to Chriſt, is accepted of God and approved by men.</p>
               <p>The Soul is and dwells in the heart, and the heart is in my body, therefore the ſoul is more neer to me then the body.</p>
               <p>My Body is cloathed with garments: hence the body is neerer to me then garments, and the ſoul neerer to me then the body: and the Spirit neerer then the ſoul, and therefore more noble, more worthy, and of more moment.</p>
               <p>And becauſe it is true, <hi>That every internall is more noble and more worthy then his externall, in which it is and dwells;</hi> that even all of us do witneſſe hilling or willing, knowing or not knowing.</p>
               <p>For behold, if we are in danger of life by fire, by water, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, or wars, &amp;c. theſe being imminent upon us, then indeed,</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, we leave behind us all our edifices, as well ſumptuous as vile, with our externall goods, and with few things, if there be any we can carry with us; we betake our ſelves to flight: ſo that the body being clad might be preſerved ſafe and unhurt, with the life and ſoul. By which very thing we teſtifie, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternalls are more deſireable then externalls. For who would be ſo fooliſh, that he would neglect, loſe and deſtroy his body for the retaining of his edifices and externall goods? when, the body being loſt and deſtroyed, edifices and externall goods are much more loſt and deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, danger preſſing, and neceſſity and ſtraights ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging us, and overwhelming us, we with <hi>John</hi> the Diſciple of Chriſt, even leave and caſt off our garments, with which we are covered, and whatſoever els is abounding to us of our ſubſtance, and naked and poor we commit our ſelves to flight, that the body only with the life and ſoul may be preſerved, and kept ſafe and ſure. Do we not by this very thing point out and ſhew that <hi>internalls are better and more greater then externalls?</hi> ſeeing that the body and life are internall, but veſtments, externall.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:165235:9"/>
               <p>And who would be of ſo perverſe a mind, that he ſhould imbrace veſtments with greater love then the body and life, and would in that mind perſiſt in danger, that he would retain and keep his garments, although he were compelled to looſe, and to deſtroy his body and life.</p>
               <p>Moreover, in perſecutions for the name of Chriſt, or for the truth, putting our body and life in danger, we even leave thoſe, and give them up to our enemies, to Tyrants, &amp;c. with patience like the Lamb of God, whom all ſheep imitate, only that the ſoul may be kept intire, ſtrong, ſafe and uncorrupt, in the faith and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and truth. Do we not ſignifie by this, that internalls prevail over externalls; becauſe the ſoul is internall, the body ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall; and who would be of ſo fooliſh a mind, that he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect and looſe his ſoul with Faith in God, and knowledge of the truth, only that he might keep his externall mortall body, and temporall life? For faith and the knowledge of the truth being deſtroyed &amp; loſt, the body with the temporall life is of no moment.</p>
               <p>Finally, in extreme torments, anguiſh and infernall dolours of our Conſcience for ſins committed, even with <hi>David</hi> we leave and execrate the very ſoul it ſelf, and we bring to nought, and empty our ſelves of al the ſo lace both of God and the creatures, and we are left unto our ſelves, crying out with the Son of God, my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me: So that God only, and alone, might be, and reman in us, unhurt, inviolated, juſt and perfect in all things that he doth with us, both ſweet, and bitter. So by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things, we are alwaies reduced to internalls, and make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to our ſelves, and unto God which is in us. Do we not therefore after this manner, teſtifie the truth of this rule. <hi>That every internall is more noble and more worthy then his exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, ſeeing there is nothing in us ſo near &amp; intimate as God is, it followes, that any other thing is not to be ſo eſteemed, ſought and loved, as God alone, who hath put and hid in us, the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Treaſure of his divine Wiſdom, Light, Life, truth and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue taken from his own ſelf, and hath commanded to ask him, ſeek, and knock in the hidden place of our heart, in Spirit, and in Truth, having given a teſtimony, that the Kingdom of God, firſt of all, to be ſought, is not here or there without us, but is to be found moſt inward in us, as a Treaſure hid in a Field.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:165235:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>From all theſe things it clearly appears to me,</hi> that God is not at all more remote or nearer to me in this life whilſt I am in this world, and in this mortall body, then he will be to me in life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, &amp;c. But I have and feel my God equally now preſent and intimate to me, even as I ſhall have him in the other world, in a new body. For he is in me, and I in him, whether I am in a mortall body in this world, or without this body in that world. This alone makes the difference, that this thing even hitherto is hidden: but then it ſhall be manifeſt and open.</p>
               <p>But that I am not ſo nigh and near to him, as he is to me, this is not to be imputed to him, but to my averſion, who do not <hi>ſabathize</hi> in my God who is with me, that is, who by running up and down with my unquite and vagabond ſoul through the creatures, I am more delighted to be and to be buſined in my proper will out of my internall Countrey; and I ſuffer that ever hiſſing Serpent to creep on to the creatures in the multifarious concupiſcence and delectation of the fleſh, of the eyes, and pride of life, or ſelf-love: neither am I leſſe frequent in the various diſcourſe of my thoughts, ever and a non day and night aſcending out of my heart, now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring this, now that, ſpeculating, willing, nilling, now this, now that; where moreover I weary and burden my ſelf with all kind of care, and vex my ſelf with various affections: All which things are the Aſtrologicall operation and revolution of the internall Starrs in our ſoul.</p>
               <p>But if I could <hi>Theologize</hi> my <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> that is, if I could deſiſt ſometimes from all theſe things, and ſtudy to be at reſt in my God who dwells with me, that is, if I could accuſtom my mind to quiet and ſpiricuall tranquillity, that it ſhould ceaſe to wander in the variety of thoughts, cares, and affections, that it might be at leiſure from the externall things and creatures of this world, and chiefly from the love of my ſelf, that I might wholly die, and as it were be anihilated in my ſelf, and could come into a loathing and oblivion, not alone of all the things of the whole world placed without me, and of mundane friendſhip, which I have with men, but alſo into a plenary dereliction of my ſelf, that is, of my will, of mine, if there be any Wiſdom, Knowledge, Science, Art, Induſtry, Prudence, of mine, if there be any dignity, praiſe, honor, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, eſtimation in the world amongſt men, of mine, if there be any Office, State, Degree, Order, and in brief, into an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165235:10"/>abſolute forgetfullneſſe of all my negociations and occupations, and of my ſelf as well within as without, which is nothing els then to <hi>Theologize Aſtrologie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then at length ſhould I begin more and more to ſee and know the moſt preſent habitation of God in me, and ſo I ſhould taſt and eat of the Tree of Life, which is in the midſt of Paradiſe, which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe <hi>I my ſelf am,</hi> as a gueſt with whom God is, and ought to be, and I in like manner with God.</p>
               <p>This I ſay, ſhould be the exerciſe of my ſoul, the <hi>theologization of Astrologie,</hi> and a regreſſion
<list>
                     <label>From</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Externalls to Internalls.</item>
                           <item>Nature to Grace.</item>
                           <item>The Creature to God.</item>
                           <item>The friendſhip of the World, to the friendſhip of God.</item>
                           <item>The tree of Death, to the tree of Life.</item>
                           <item>Terrene things to Celeſtiall.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>So ſhould I go again to my firſt originall, from whence I went forth, by arrogating to my ſelf a liberty of willing, deſiring, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, thinking, ſpeaking and doing what I pleaſed me, God in the mean time being neglected, without whom I ought not to do any thing.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever therefore we have from the Light of Nature, all this with moſt humble ſelf-deniall once in the week is to be laid down at the feet of the beſt and greateſt God, whether it be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gic, or Gabaliſtic, or Aſtronomic, or Chimic, or Medicinall, or Phiſicall Science: Alſo Liberall Arts, and Methanick work, and whatſoever Study, Office, State, Order, Dignity, Kind of life, alſo Wealth, Riches, Houſes, and all kind of naturall gifts: All theſe appertain to this our Aſtrologie, and ought ſo to be Theologized, by the exerciſe of ſanctifying the Sabbath, which is an univerſall forgetfullneſſe of all things and of our ſelves, and the reſt of our ſoul from all diſquiet, in a ſacred ſilence, a ceſſation from all will, thought, deſire, affection, diſcourſe, operation, &amp;c. as well within, as without. And this is that only and principall cauſe of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths being divinely commanded to Man: to wit, that man ſhould not eat death and periſh to himſelf by the eating of the forbidden Tree.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To eat,</hi> is to be delighted in himſelf and in the creatures, rather then in the Creator himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:165235:11"/>
               <p>To kiſſe himſelf in the gift received,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>1. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>2. 1.</hi> John <hi>2.6.</hi> Mat. <hi>2.</hi> Gen. <hi>20.</hi> Exod.</note> neglecting the giver.</p>
               <p>To love the world, and things which are in the world, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting God.</p>
               <p>To ſerve Mammon neglecting God.</p>
               <p>To uſe all things after his pleaſure and will, diſpiſing the Law of the Lord. Thou ſhalt not covet, thou ſhalt not eat, thou ſhalt not deſire to turn himſelf from God to the creatures, and to himſelf. To commit whoredom with the creatures. To depend on himſelf, and on things created. To languiſh in love of terrene things, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall good things; ſetting God aſide, which may be deſcribed a thouſand waies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> who came from above, and brings celeſtiall and divine Wiſdom from the <hi>Light of Grace,</hi> ſounds alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether contrary, to wit,</p>
               <p>That a man ought to be converted into a child, and to have ſo much of the knowledge of good and evill to live in him, as he had when he was but a child, or infant newly born.</p>
               <p>I ſay the Doctrine of Chriſt commands a man to eat of the Tree of life, to live by the inſpiration of the internall God-head, which is,</p>
               <p>To fall off again from the creatures, and from himſelf to God.</p>
               <p>To adhere to God, Mammon being left.</p>
               <p>To be united with God, the love of the creatures being left.</p>
               <p>To believe in God, to offer, and to give up himflef to God, to pray; thy will be done, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To put off the old Man, and to put on the new Man.</p>
               <p>To flie evill, and adhere to good, which in like ſort may be explicated by a thouſand manner of ſpeakings, and phraſes from the very writings of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in what manner all, and ſingular kinds of ſciences,</hi> and naturall gifts, and thoſe vain ſtudies, actions, buſineſſes and differences of men, &amp;c. ariſe from the Light of Nature, or the Starrs; and in what order they are referred to the ſeven Governours of the world, and how a man ought to uſe them: alſo how every one of us ought to <hi>Theologize</hi> his own <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> flouriſhing in himſelf, and to erect to himſelf a new nativity, from the heaven of the new Creature, and to inſtitute and aſſume a new kind of life: and chiefly, what is the ſolid and the moſt certain cauſe of all of the holy Sabbath, that is, after what manner a man ought to labour ſix daies, and on the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165235:11"/>ſeventh day to ſanctifie the Sabbath rightly. All theſe things are moſt evidently ſet forth and propounded in the following Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of the compoſition of the Microcoſme, that is Man, from the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, the great World</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ADam</hi> the firſt parent of the whole humane kind, was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and formed by the admirable wiſdom, and workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, <hi>as to his ſoul and body of the ſlime, or duſt of the earth;</hi> which <hi>ſlime or duſt</hi> was ſuch a Maſſe or matter, which had conjoyned and compoſed in it ſelf the univerſall eſſence, nature, vertue and propriety <hi>of the whole greater World, and of all things which were therein. I ſay that Maſſe, ſlime or dust was a meer quinteſſence, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from every part, from the whole frame of the whole world;</hi> from which ſlime or Maſſe, was made ſuch a creature, with it's form ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, was one and the ſame with the great world, of which it was produced. Hence that creature was called Man, who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his admirable creation &amp; formation being revealed amongſt the wiſe, was wont moſt fitly to be called the <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> that is, the little, or leſſe world.</p>
               <p>The abſolute deſcription, and eſſentiall explication of this <hi>ſlime,</hi> duſt or maſſe extracted from the whole macrocoſme, we ſhall find every where abundantly and wonderfully declared, alone by <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophraſtus Paracelſus</hi> in his moſt excellent writings.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore it is manifeſt, that every produced and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing, can take or aſſume his eſſence, nature and propriety from nothing els, but from that where of it is made and produced; which even that firſt Man, <hi>as an other and later World,</hi> made of the former World, by the <hi>Ens</hi> of that <hi>ſlime,</hi> is made pertaker of the ſame eſſence, nature &amp; propriety, as the Macrocoſme had in it ſelf. For the whole great world exiſting and being compact in that quinteſſence of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted ſlime, forthwith it followed, that the whole Macrocoſme was complicitly collected and tranſpoſed into man, by divine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the ſubſtance and nature of the Macrocoſme remaining ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe ſafe and intire. For ſuch is the condition in the univerſal production and generation of things, <hi>that every like of it ſelf produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his like, and that without destruction of its eſſence and nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence, that which hath its originall and derivation from God,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165235:12"/>is the ſame that God is;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3. John</hi> That which is born of the Spirit is Spirit. That which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh.</note> 
                  <hi>The Spirit or breath of God which is in Man immidiately proceeds from God, therefore God is of a truth in Man by the Ens of inſpiration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which hath its originall and derivation from the world, is the ſame that the world is. <hi>The ſoul and body of man are immediately taken, extracted, and compoſed of the World,</hi> therefore the world is of a truth in Man, by the Ens of ſlime.</p>
               <p>So the firſt Man made of the Macrocoſme, bears in himſelf the Macrocoſme, with the eſſence and nature of all creatures compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, collected and compacted together: yet nevertheleſſe, he formed us to his body of the Elements and things elementated: as to his ſoul of the ſoul of the Macrocoſme, or the Spirit of Nature which contains and comprehends in himſelf the whole Firmament, with all its Starrs, and aſtralique vertues and operations: So it comes to paſſe, <hi>That there is nothing without a man in the whole hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Nature, and in all the Elements, with which man in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition doth not participate, and is endued with its Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there are two things in which the Microcoſme and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme differ and appear to be contrary, to wit,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The forme of the perſon, and the complication of things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the form, it ſeemed good to divine wiſdom to convert that Maſſe extracted from the Macrocoſme, and to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a man, not to put and ſet it into the form of the Macrocoſme, which is round and circular: Nor according to the animall form: But it pleaſed him to erect and apply it to the <hi>form of his own Image and ſimilitude.</hi> Man nevertheleſſe in the mean time remaining the Macrocoſme.</p>
               <p>Therefore this difference doth not touch his eſſence.</p>
               <p>The form doth not take away the truth of the ſubject, that man may not be believed to be the Macrocoſme.</p>
               <p>As to the complication or compoſition of all naturall things, <hi>into one body, or into one perſon;</hi> all things cannot be apparent and diſtinctly known together in a Man; one thing after an other, as it is excited and provoked,<note place="margin">See concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Wiſdom by <hi>Paracelſus.</hi>
                  </note> is manifeſt and flouriſheth in the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> other things in the mean time remaining hid in the Macrocoſme, all things are explicitly exiſting, living and operating in the <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies:</hi> But in the Macrocoſme all things are compact and conjoyned together.</p>
               <p>Moreover after that Man the Microcoſme was, and held all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165235:12"/>things now in himſelf, out of which he was taken, behold <hi>the whole plenitude of Nature,</hi> as well corporally as ſpiritually was conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in him, and as a moſt rich Treaſure collected and laid up in one Centre, yet ſo as man ſhould be all things complicitly; and yet none of them all explicitly.</p>
               <p>And from this Protop laſt, or firſt formed man and begetter of all, even in like manner are we conſtituted and formed:<note place="margin">Adam <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> not of the ſame ſlime or Maſſe as that was in the beginning, whereof <hi>Adam</hi> was made: But by a Maſſe extracted from the ſubſtance of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme, which we with <hi>Paracelſus</hi> call the <hi>Ens of ſeed,</hi> which ſeed hath and bears in it ſelf complicitly the whole Macrocoſme, that is, Man, and thence the humane off-ſpring, as to the eſſence, nature and propriety in all things a like grows and comes forth to its begetter, as a moſt lively image, which truly could not be done if all theſe things did not lie hid, &amp; were extant in the <hi>Ens</hi> of the ſeed. Hence <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of us</hi> hath the ſame in himſelf eſſentially delivered over to himſelf by the <hi>Ens of the ſeed</hi> from his parent: which the firſt man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and had from the extracted Macrocoſme by the <hi>Ens of ſlime,</hi> to wit, an elemental body from the Elements, and a ſoul or ſydere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſpirit from the Firmament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> That all kinds of Sciences, Studies, Actions and lifes flouriſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men on the earth and Sea do testifie, That all Aſtrologie, that is, naturall wiſdom, with all it's ſpecies, is and is to be really found in every man: And ſo all things whatſoever men act on earth is produced, moved, governed and acted from the inward heaven. And what are the Starrs which a wiſe man ought to rule.</head>
               <p>IT is manifeſt therefore by the aboveſaid, how man appeareth to be made at length as to his Creation and Formation of ſlime, that is, from the Macrocoſme.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe Man the Macrocoſme placed in the Macrocoſme, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth altogether as well with the whole Firmament, as with all the Elements, and is one and the ſame (his form only excepted) as we ſee redneſſe to be altogether one and the ſame in wine, &amp; with wine, and whiteneſſe in ſnow and with ſnow.</p>
               <p>Then it followeth: Seeing Man for himſelf and in himſelf is the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165235:13"/>whole world, as he which hath his proper Heaven, his proper Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, and Spirit of Nature, with the Sun, Moon, Planets, and all the Starrs with him in himſelf, of which <hi>from within</hi> he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellated, inclined, directed, moved, excited, drawn, turned, gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, taught, illuminated, made joyfull, made ſad is fortunate, and affected: It is manifeſt, that he is in no wiſe forced and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by the externall Firmament of the Macrocoſme, our ſoul of the world, that he ſhould aſſume and take a mind and affections, of willing, doing, and operating this or that from without, from the revolution, and inclination, or conſtellation of the celeſtiall Starrs in the Macrocoſme.</p>
               <p>For their opinion is of no moment, who not rightly knowing the Macrocoſme, are fallen into that errour, that they doubt not to determin: That man by the externall influence of the Starrs, by a certain naturall neceſſity is conditioned, predeſtinated, conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, directed, compelled, and driven to this or that good, or evill, <hi>Hence thoſe falſe Proverbs; the Starrs incline; the Starrs rule men.</hi> which is in no ſort ſo, if according to their opinion it be underſtood of the externall Starrs.</p>
               <p>But we muſt know, that all things whatſoever that are done by men, as well in ſoul, as in body, ariſe and proceed from within, from their own proper inclination and nature.</p>
               <p>Within, I ſay, in man is that Heaven, that Planet, that Sydus or Starr, by which he is inclined, conſtituted, predeſtinated and ſigned to this or that, and not from without, by the conſtitution of the externall Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that ſaying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A wiſe man will rule the Starrs.</note> 
                  <hi>a wiſe man ſhall rule the Starrs:</hi> is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the externall Starrs, in the Heaven or Firmament of the great World; but of the internall Starrs, bearing ſway and running up and down in man himſelf, which will more and more appear by that which followeth. But this we promiſe for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to be noted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the externall Heaven with it's continuall revolution, hath a most convenient correſpondency with the inward Heaven in the Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, and this with that,</hi> which you may thus underſtand.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever the ſigure of the externall Heaven is, in the point of conception of any men, which happens in the matrix of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by the <hi>Ens of ſeed,</hi> even now ſent forth from Man; that Man which is born and grows from that ſeed, receiveth from within
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165235:13"/>ſuch a conſtitution of his nature and life to be performed on earth.</p>
               <p>Yet that conſtitution lies ſo long hid and unknown, that is, without act in a naked power, untill a man born into the world and educated to the uſe of free-will, and reaſon, putting forth it ſelf, begins to be moved and incited. For then, and not before, that conſtitution of his heaven, begins by little and little, to roll, bring forth, move, and ſhew forth it ſelf, when the Aſcendants of that ſigure, by the imagination and fantaſie, newly ſprung up in the will and reaſon, ariſe and proceed to the motion of the mind, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the body. And ſo the internall Heaven in the Microcoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me begins his motion and courſe, that a man from within, <hi>from the guidance of his own Nature,</hi> begins to imagine, think, deſire, hear, ſpeak, do the ſame thing which before was ſignified, from the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the externall Heaven, while he was conceived.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>the externall heaven in the Macrocoſme,</hi> as it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Man, is at leaſt a looking glaſſe and perludium, by which the Aſtrologer may look into, ſearch, know, and deſcribe what and what kind of nature and propriety ſhall happen, and rule in him, from the beginning of his nativity, to the end of his life, as he ſhall live Aſtrologically, and not Theologically; what and what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner his imagination ſhall be, what his affections, what his cupidities, what his deſires, what his manners, what his ſtudy, what his kind of life and death, with what things he ſhall be moſt delighted, and on the contrary, with what he ſhall be adverſe, and all things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſeem to belong to the condition of humane life. This I ſay, may from the poſition or erected ſigure of the externall heaven be prognoſticated &amp; foretold, not that thoſe things are ſo done by neceſſity or coactive force: but only that thoſe things are preſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, and as it were preludiated, and are indeed a certain picture of humane life, as in like ſort a certain living man is painted by a painter on the wall, from which picture his ſpecies and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with all his habit, is exhibited and declared to be known: So alſo we men living according to the courſe of nature, and not Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gizing our Aſtrologie are known, deſcribed and diſcovered by an Aſtrologer from the Table ſigure, face and concordance of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Firmament, as by a looking glaſſe.</p>
               <p>For living naturally, we have from the figure of Heaven a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſcription of our life, whether it be honeſt or diſhoneſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertuous or vicious: Yet ſo as the impulſive or efficient cauſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165235:14"/>of living thus, or ſo, may not be thought to proceed and be impreſſed on man from the externall Heaven, but from within, from our internall Heaven, which is in our ſoul delighted, with this or that manner of living. For neither God nor the Macrocoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me do compell or force man (placed in the midſt) from without, to this or that good or evill kind of life, by a certain naturall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: but that very thing which is put into us by God, and by the Macrocoſme, that is it whereby we are led, whereby we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellated, moved,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>6.</hi> Galat. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> inſtigated, ſtirred up, invited, governed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined.</p>
               <p>The one is the Spirit of God, the breath of God, the deity and heavenly light, the holy Spirit, the mind of God.</p>
               <p>The other is the Spirit of Nature, the breath of the World, the Light of Nature, the affections of the fleſh, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrene Wiſdom, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimall Man, the Syderean Spirit, the reaſon of Man.</p>
               <p>Both leads to their originall, and ſheweth what are theirs.</p>
               <p>Our Nature inſtigates, moves, and leadeth to our naturalls: But the Spirit of God, which we have in us from God, inſtigates, moves, urgeth and leads us to ſupernaturalls, that is, thither whence he himſelf is.</p>
               <p>There are I ſay, two Inſpirers, two Governours, two Captains, two Lords in us, to whom none of us can equally ſerve. The one tends to the ſtraight way, to inherit and poſſeſſe the Kingdom of Heaven, by contempt of the world, and deniall of our ſelves: the other neglecting the Kingdom of God, to enter into the broad way. The one is of God which is the Theologicall Spirit, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and perſwading the Theologicall life to Man: the other is from <hi>Nature,</hi> from the World, which is the Aſtrologicall Spirit, propounding and perſwading the Aſtrologicall life to Man.</p>
               <p>The Theologicall Spirit, being endued with ſupernaturall Light, and Wiſdom, ſhews the Kingdom of God, and eternall life.</p>
               <p>But the Aſtrologicall Spirit endowed with naturall Wiſdom and Light, ſhews the ſhop of Nature, and the glory of this world; therefore thoſe which are acted by the Spirit of God, theſe are the Sons of God, that is, who live Theologically: But they which are acted and led by the Spirit of Nature (caring nothing for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and the eternall Countrey) theſe are the ſons of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſons of this world, animall men, not doing the will of God, but the will of the fleſh: in which with all their glory and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165235:14"/>magnificence, they whoſoever they are, how great ſoever they are, and whereſoever they are, muſt periſh. For without the Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation of Aſtrologie, no mortall man can attain eternall ſalvation and beatitude. We muſt die once to fleſh and bloud, and to the whole animall Man, and we muſt live to God; which life is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether contrary to the worldly life. Of which more largely in the <hi>Epiſtles of Paul,</hi> and other <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Starrs which a wiſe man is commanded to rule,</hi> are not thoſe celeſtiall Starrs extant in the Firmament of the Macrocoſme, which are ſet before the Creatour of the Elements, that they might illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the earth, and be for ſigns and ſeaſons, and rule over the day and the night; thoſe have their peculiar Regent, Lord and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, to wit, the Spirit or ſoul of the world diffuſed into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Planets, and the reſt of the Stars of the whole Zodiac, by which he exerciſeth his rule, hath his influx into inferiour things: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no cauſe that any ſhould through ſimplicity, think the dominion which a wiſe man hath over the Starrs, belongs to the moderation of the externall Firmament; as if a wiſe man ought to rule the courſe of the Celeſtiall Starrs and ſigns, and to reduce the frame of the Macrocoſme under his power, to direct &amp; govern the Sun, Moon, Planets, and Starrs according to his pleaſure, and to make calme and tempeſtuous weather according to his will. Not ſo,</p>
               <p>But the Starrs over which we ought to rule, if we wil be true wiſe men, are all the cogitations, ſpeculations, cupidities, affections, &amp;c. aſcending by imagination out of our hearts, reſpecting the things and creatures of the world, and tending by free will and reaſon to abuſe and pleaſure: to them we ought not to be too much adicted, or overmuch to connive and indulge. For in theſe that deadly and infernall ſnake or ſerpent lieth hid, ſeducing man by all ſort of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences into an unlawfull love, honour, and worſhip of the creatures, and thereof makes a Babiloniſh whore, as in the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent matter will be demonſtrated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:165235:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Touching a double Firmament and Starr in every man, and that by the benefit of Regeneration in the exerciſe of the Sabbath, a man may be tranſpoſed from a worſer Nature into a better.</head>
               <p>FRom the aboveſaid, there appears a moſt elegant Doctrine, to wit, although ſome of us by conſtitution and concordance of the externall and internall heaven, in the point of his conception and nativity, ſhould happily have attained the moſt wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation and nature, ready and prone to commit any kind of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſſe: ſo as he ſhould even bear in his face, in his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, in his hands, and in his whole body, an evident ſignature or phiſiognomie to every moſt wicked crime, all which, ſhould ſhew moſt certain tokens that he ſhould act, not only a moſt miſerable and moſt wicked kind of life; but alſo ſhould expect on himſelf the moſt cruell puniſhment and deſtruction: Yet nevertheleſſe we muſt not altogether deſpair of ſuch a mans correction and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The reaſon is,</p>
               <p>Becauſe beſides the naturall Heaven, and Aſtralic Firmament which is in our ſoul, we have another Heaven, another Sydus, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Starr, another Light, another Conſtellation, which is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, by whoſe power being ſupported, we may ſhake off, and drive away all the provocations of the evill aſcendents of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Starrs, as an Aſſe is wont to ſhake off, and drive away flies and gnats ſtinging him on his back.</p>
               <p>Therefore although nature is potent and ſtrong in her ſelf, in inciting and forcing a man in his proper will and reaſon, by her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and delectable concupiſcences to any kind of crime: Yet the Spirit of the Lord in his vertue, power, and fortitude, is far ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and exceeds nature in as great a meaſure as the Sun is ſeen to excell the Moon. Let a man then at length learn, and do his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that he may know what that moſt profitable precept of God, <hi>touching the ſanctification of the Sabbath</hi> to be exerciſed,<note place="margin">Sibi velit</note> every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day requires of him, in which exerciſe, nevertheleſſe, the worſt of things may be corrected, and alſo transformed into the beſt things: For ſuch a <hi>medicine</hi> lyeth hid in the holy exerciſe of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as whole Nature with her univerſall vertue is not able to exhibit to a man; for which medicines ſake this book is written</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:165235:15"/>
               <p>A man therefore inclined naturally, to this or that vice, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his generation, ought not to connive at himſelf, or to frame any excuſe, as if he could by right accuſe the externall heaven, that that is the cauſe, wherefore he cannot live honeſtly, and do that which is good, nor by any means can overcome, change, break, correct his ſinful nature, or convert it into better, and ſo under the pretext of humane imbecillity, as it were, defend his ſpontaneous malice, avarice, luſt, pride and intemperance, &amp;c. and to go forward in a vicious life.</p>
               <p>O opinion moſt worthy of refutation, and to be acurſed! I pray what ſhould the cry of Chriſt, the Prophets and Apoſtles avail? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, repent, be ye converted unto me, and I will be converted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, put off the old Man, and put on the new Man, and flie evill, and cleave to that which is good, and lay aſide the works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and walk in the light. I ſay to what end ſhould theſe things be ſpoken and commanded, if our defence or excuſe ſhould have place in the divine Judgement?</p>
               <p>Let ſuch a man the refore ſo wickedly deceived of himſelf, ſuffer himſelf to be inſtructed and taught by this our moſt profitable The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologization of Aſtrologie, wherein we have found and tryed, not without the greateſt joy of the mind, that beſides the ſhop and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of nature, there is alwaies preſent in us ſomething far more great and excellent, with the knowledge and vertue whereof we being fraught, have power of reſiſting not only one, but all vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as well the greateſt, as the leaſt, whatſoever lie hid and are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in us: Yea, power not only of caſting down, and drowning one ſtone, but alſo the whole mountain of the Macrocoſme being in us, in the Sea of divine Power, or extirpating utterly, not only one leafe, but even the whole tree of the knowledge of good and evill extant in us, and of tranſplanting it into the garden of the celeſtiall Paradiſe.</p>
               <p>For ſo all theſe things are manifeſt in Theologicall miſteries, to thoſe that underſtand theſe things. <hi>Truly it is evident, all things are eſſentially to be transferred unto Man, which are divinely written for Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, we have a power lying hid in us of over ruling whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">See the Scripture of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth.</note> of ſtopping the Serpent, and overcoming all his force, and of inſtituting in us a new, and that good, a better, the beſt nativity of erecting and inſtituting in us, from a new heaven, a new kind of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165235:16"/>life, and a far more happy ſigure, and that by the ſole benefit of the Sabbath; by which from day to day we may put off the old Man, and put on the new Man, fall back from vices, and paſſe on to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that is, to ſhake off from us all the aſcendent Starrs, or flames of divers concupiſcences and deſires to all kind of pleaſures of this world, ever and anon provoking, drawing, and ſeducing us.</p>
               <p>By this means we go forth ſafe and free from the houſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, from the Babilonian Captivity, and we eſcape from the power of the great Creature, we overcome ſinfull nature, we reſiſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, we chaſe away the divell. And by how much the more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent we are in this exerciſe of the Sabbath, or in this Theologiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Aſtrologie: by ſo much the more we are made ſtrangers to Nature, that we are ſcarce any more known or touched by her, neither doth any Aſtrologer, Phiſiognomour, Signatour, Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, Artiſt how induſtrious ſoever, know any more to erect any certain nativity, or to prognoſticate any thing to come. Becauſe they which are frequent in familiarity with God, theſe are more and more alienated from the world, that they are not any more ſaid to be of the world,<note place="margin">John <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> but of heaven, although as to the body, they are as yet converſant in the world. And whatſoever any one doth by the Sabbath, in the introverſion of his mind, he acts and orders with God, and God with him, in the hidden place of his heart, this cannot be ſeen or known by any Spirit: much leſſe by Man.</p>
               <p>In brief, by the Sabbath alone, the Phenix of our ſoul is renewed, who altogether denying, depoſing, refuſing and accompting for nothing, all the vanity of this world, and it ſelf from within and without, plainly dies in the forgetfullneſſe and contempt of all things,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> and of it ſelf, and offers it ſelf a living and pleaſing ſacrifice to God, and there being regenerate anew, becomes a new creature, a new off-ſpring from the ſeed of the woman, by conception from the holy Spirit is made a Son of God, a new Man, an imitatour of Chriſt, following his ſteps, is made a hater of evill, and a follower of good, a new plant, a new tree that is good, which brings forth good fruits, this is true repentance, true penitence, the true putting off the old Man, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here ſome Aſtrologers are to be admoniſhed of their want of knowledge, who have not doubted to ſubject even the whole man, with all things which are in him, to the dominion of the world and Starrs, in erecting their nativities, as if a man were, or had no more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165235:16"/>in himſelf then a bruit or beaſt, through ignorance paſſing by the conſtitution of Man in three parts, <hi>Spirit, Soul and Body;</hi> whoſe ſoul ariſing from the Firmamentall Zodiac, and whoſe body from the Elements, are altogether ſubject to the dominion of Nature: But not the Spirit which we have from God; and liſtning nothing to that, that every Diſciple of Chriſt, and friend of God, regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from above, by faith and the death of ſin in the moſt holy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, hath within himſelf, a moſt preſent medicine in his heart, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the poiſonous and deadly wounds of nature, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; and alſo the divine Commandement of depoſing, overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and conquering the old heaven, with his inclinations of divers concupiſcences, and of walking in the newneſſe of the Spirit, in the Light of Grace.</p>
               <p>To wiſemen therefore, that is, to thoſe that know both God and themſelves rightly, the matter is far better to be looked into, for they know both are in us.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>God, and Nature.</item>
                  <item>The Kingdom of Heaven, and the Kingdom of the world.</item>
                  <item>The Tree of Life, and the Tree of Death.</item>
                  <item>The greater Light, and the leſſer Light.</item>
                  <item>The ſeed of the Woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And alſo that man is placed between theſe two, to be exerciſed in this world in a perpetual war: whether of theſe ſhould overcome, thence ſhall man have his reward, for God will render to every one, all crafty excuſe and imbecillity being laid aſide, &amp;c. according to his works, whether they be good or evill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here you ſhall obſerve an example, touching the change of man from an inferiour and worſer nature, into a ſuperiour and better nature.</hi> If you take a certain ſtone, lying by chance in a ſunny place, and very much heated by the too much parching heat of the Sun, and put it into water, or ſome river, then the Sun can no more make it ſo hot, or penetrate it with his heat; in like manner the caſe is, in the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologization of Aſtrologie.<note n="*" place="margin">The exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Sabbath, or Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gization of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, is to dic to thy ſelf and the whole creature, to offer thy ſelf wholly to God, with all things which are within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us. Hither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and all books, ſpeaking of the mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Man.</note> Take or gather, and apprehend all thy evill nature, and thy unſincere affections, and unlawfull luſts, too much operating and flouriſhing in thee, I ſay take and put them by the Sabbath, into the mind or ſpirit of thy mind, which thou haſt from God, who is the everlaſting fountain and water of life, and ſabathize in a ſolid and conſtant abnegation of thy ſelf, and of all things known unto thee, which are within thee, as well as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165235:17"/>without thee, that thou maiſt almoſt wholly die there; then will thy ſoul with all her adherent ſtones of concupiſcences, fall down and be drowned in the depth of the ſupernall water, which is the Spirit of God infuſed in us, and the firmamentall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration will more and more ceaſe and be wearied in thee, and the aſcendant Starrs of thy concupiſcences, will no more afflict, urge, drive, carry thee as before: but from day to day, thou ſhalt eaſe thy ſelf from that moſt hard yoke of the Zodiac, and of all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, thy youth ſhall be renewed as an Eagle, and thou ſhalt be like an infant new-born, and ſhalt perceive in thy ſelf new vertues, and affections to work and move in thee, ariſing, inclining, oecupying, leading and governing thee from the celeſtiall Starr, and influence of the divine Spirit, &amp;c. So as where heretofore, thou haſt bin the ſervant of ſin, and haſt given thy members weapons of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and malice, now with trembling thou abhorreſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of thy forepaſt life, and fraught with a new mind, heart, affections and deſire, from the exerciſe of the Sabbath, by the Spirit of God; hereafter thou ſhalt ſerve God, and give up thy members weapons of juſtice, piety, charity, mercy, meekneſſe, temperance, modeſty, chaſtity, &amp;c. and ſo thou ſhalt rightly Theologize thy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, ſo ſhalt thou beſt overcome, correct, amend thy nature, ſo ſhalt thou rightly tread the head of the Serpent under thy feet, ſo ſhalt thou well ſilence in thy ſelf the aſſaults of the divell, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hence the true Sabbath inſtituted and commanded of God, is the beſt care and medicine againſt all kind of evill, which quickly being death eternall to the ſoul, and temporall to the body, by which we may put off, bear and take off that great and moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous yoke and mountain of ſo great a Zodiac, of ſo great a Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of ſo great Governours. I ſay to take away the Kingdom or rule, and to precipitate into the immenſe Sea of eternall water, and ever and anon get new ſtrength, and come out more vivacious, which was well known and uſed by the Patriarchs in the firſt age, whence alſo they could get to themſelves the Enochian long life upon earth, by the exerciſe of this kind of mentall Sabbath, which indeed is altogether obliterated, abrogated in this our age, and ſeems to be a thing unknown.</p>
               <p>But how every one of us ought, and may know, and try in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, what and what kind truly is their Aſtrologie, or firmamentall action or operation of the Light of Nature; and how he may and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165235:17"/>can Theologize the ſame, that is, overcome Nature be made the Son of God, &amp;c. this the following Chapters will illuſtrate, and teach more clearly then the Sun.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Touching the diſtribution of all Aſtrologie, into the ſeven Governours of the world, and their operations and offices, as well in the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, as in the Microcoſme.</head>
               <p>THe whole ſhop of Nature, with all her ſorts of ſciences and actions, is ordained and diſtributed into ſeven chief members, Kingdoms or Dominions, according to the ſeven Aſtra's of the Planets of the ☉, of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, of ☿ of ♀, of ♂, of ♃, of ♄, who are the Governours of all naturall things, extant in the whole frame of the world, by the foure Elements.</p>
               <p>But the Light of Nature which we call Aſtrologie, is nothing els, then the very life, vigour, vertue, action and operation of the whole world, in things which proceed and come forth from the <hi>ſoul of the world, or the spirit of the Firmament,</hi> whoſe ſeat is in the body of the Sun. For there the ſoul of the world, or the ſpirit of the Macrocoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me dwells; as the ſoul of the Microcoſme in the heart, and in the Sun it is moſt potent, whence it diffuſeth his vertues, actions and powers, out of it ſelf ever and anon into the other ſix Planets, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, ☿, ♀, ♂, ♃, ♄: And moreover in all the other Starrs, being throughout the whole ſtelliferous Chaos.</p>
               <p>By this only ſoul the whole world lives, is governed, agitated and moved, as a body by his ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Sun is the heart and light of the world,</hi> in this heart I ſay the ſoul inhabits, which illuminates all and every the Planets and Stars, upwards above it ſelf, and downwards beneath it ſelf, as well in the day as in the night time, and diſperſes his power into all and ſingular bodies, as well the ſuperiour things to the utmoſt ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the frame, as alſo the inferiour things even to the inward Centre in the earth. Yea, the <hi>Sun</hi> by his vertue paſſeth through all corporealls like unto glaſſe,<note place="margin">The power and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sun.</note> and operates in them without any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment.</p>
               <p>So his force penetrates the whole body of the Sea as glaſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any obſtacle, even to the loweſt bottom thereof: So the whole
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:165235:18"/>body of the earth, full of pores on every ſide, is paſſable to the Sun, even to the inward point of his Circle. So the Sun fills the ſphear of Air: alſo the Sphears of Heaven; and enters into views, and poſſeſſeth with his power all the Angels of all the regions and parts of the world, as the ſoul doth his body of the Microcoſme, and not only the Chaos and the bodies of Elements, but alſo all the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſubſtances of all things whenceſoever exiſting, as well ſubtile as groſſe, as well light as heavy, as well ſoft as hard, mettalls, mountains, hills, gemms, rocks, ſtones, wood, and whatſoever is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, ſo as it reacheth to the very Centre of the earth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his force and operation wanting, or deficient there: For all bodies though never ſo great, groſſe, thick, are altogether as glaſſe, to the penetrative power of the Sun: and although our eyes do not ſo expreſſely know and ſee this preſent ingreſſive, penetrating, ſubtile and active power of the Sun in all things, but the groſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies alwaies are and remain in our eyes groſſe, dark, ſhady: Yet in reſpect of the Sun, and to the vertue of the Sun after their manner, all things are diaphane, and perſpicuous, and penetrable. Which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vertue thruſts forth and produceth all things hid in the earth: and as the Air is ſuch, that with the very vertue of the Sun, it doth eſſentially enter into all bodies, penetrate and fill all things. For fire is the life of things,<note place="margin">Liſe is fire.</note> no fire can burn, that is, live without Air, whereſoever therefore there is life or fire, or the vertue of the Sun, there alſo is Air.<note place="margin">The world a great Creature.</note> Now the whole greater world, as to its ſoul and body with all the creatures that are therein, is one Creature by it ſelf, and one animall, and lives like an animall, having in it ſelf its vitall ſpirit, endued with a ſevenfold operation, or diffuſed into the ſeven Planets, into all the Starrs, and into all the Elements, and all vegetables, Mineralls and animalls generated of Elements. The Element <hi>of Fire</hi> hath his ſhop or ſeat in the body of the Sun, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and all the Starrs: in that fire <hi>the Phenix of the world,</hi> or ſoul of the world dwells, which operates all things, and is the Light of Nature, the Vulcan of Heaven, the Arthens of Nature.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Air is it's reſpiration and balſome.</item>
                  <item>The Water is it's blood.</item>
                  <item>The Earth is it's fleſh.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In like manner alſo it is in the <hi>Minor World</hi> in Man, who as to his ſoul and body (the form excepted) in all things anſwers to the Major World, as a ſon to his father, becauſe taken out of him, and placed in him.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:165235:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the heart,</hi> is the ſeat or habitation of the ſoul of the little world, or the Syderean Spirits, whoſe vertue, life, motion, nature, force, operation, ever and anon by going forth, diffuſeth it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other ſix principall members of the Microcoſme, <hi>the Brain, the Liver, the Lungs, the Gall, the Spleen, the Reins,</hi> and from thence into the whole body, and all the muſcles, veins, nerves, parts and extremities of the whole Microcoſme; and ſo that only ſoul reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the heart, carries, governs, agitates, leads, moves the whole body, according to the nature and propriety of theſe ſeven prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall members; by which the body performs all his works, as well artificiall and ſubtile, as ſimple and rude. As the ſoule of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme labouring in the ſeven Governours of his body, and the reſt of the Starrs produceth all created things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore as to the concordance of</hi> theſe ſeven Governours, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Starrs, or vertues in the Major and Minor World, it is certain, that
<list>
                     <item>1. The Heart. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 1. ☉ In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                     <item>2. The Brain. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 2. <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                     <item>3. The Lungs. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 3. ☿ In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                     <item>4. The Reins. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 4. ♀ In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                     <item>5. The Gall. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 5. ♂ In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                     <item>6. The Liver. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 6. ♃ In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                     <item>7. The Spleen. In the Microcoſme is the ſame, and hath the ſame force, that as 7. ♄ In the Macrocoſme.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And as to the Elements.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Fleſh. Hath his anatomy of the Microcoſme. 1. The Earth. Of the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme.</item>
                  <item>2. The Blood. Hath his anatomy of the Microcoſme. 2. The Water. Of the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme.</item>
                  <item>3. The Reſpiration. Hath his anatomy of the Microcoſme. 3. The Air. Of the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme.</item>
                  <item>4. The Heat. Hath his anatomy of the Microcoſme. 4. The Fire. Of the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For in the Fleſh of the Microcoſme lyeth hid the eſſence, nature and propriety of all vegetables ſpringing out of the earth, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and diſperſed throughout the whole body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Blood,</hi> doth exiſt the eſſence, nature and propriety of all mineralls and mettalls bred of water, diſperſed throughout the whole region of the blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Reſpiration,</hi> whoſe ſeat is in the Lungs, the Bowells, and the Veins, and all pores, mirſcles, &amp;c. is the eſſence, nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of all the airy creatures, diſperſed through the whole body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Heat</hi> dwells the eſſence, nature, force, operation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of all the Starrs, and conſtellations of Starrs, diſperſed-through the whole body.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:165235:19"/>
               <p>Moreover, as to the concordance of either Light, as well in the Major as in the Minor world, thus it is.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever things man living on earth hath found out, firſt the oretically, by ſpeculating, meditating, ſearching and inquiring, excogitating from within in his heart, and after by his free will or deſire produceth endeavours, attempts, inſtitutes, handles, operates and transferrs to practice in whatſoever kind of Sciences, Arts, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, (Theologie excepted which is not a humane invention) ſtudies, handyworks, labours and negotiations, whether they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to good or evill,<note place="margin">Or alſo the fruit of the Tree of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evill, which is evident only to Magies.</note> all theſe comprehended under one name, are called <hi>the Light of Nature; or Aſtrologie or naturall Wiſdome ariſing from the naturall heaven, or Firmament and Starrs:</hi> That wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and that light is in the ſoul of Man, dwelling and working in the heart, which if it be exalted in its power given to it, and created in it, can do the ſame, and more, then the ſoul of nature in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme, whoſe ſeat is in the Sun; becauſe Man the Microcoſme is the quinteſſence, extracted from the Macrocoſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſeeing all and ſingular Sciences,</hi> Arts, Faculties, Orders, States, kinds of life, and ſtudies flouriſhing amongſt men on the earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and proceed from an internall inviſible Heaven, Firmament, Starr and Light of Nature, in the Microcoſme, which is extracted from the Light, Heaven, Firmament and Starr of the Macrocoſme, and hath his ſingular anatomy, diſtribution and conveniencie to the offices and operations of the ſeven Governours of the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: We as the order of thoſe Governours extant in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heaven, is expoſed to our eyes, will firſt of all handle <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, occupying the Supreme ſphear,</hi> to wit, <hi>what is the Theorie and practiſe of</hi> his Heaven, Starr or Conſtellation, with his adjunct Starrs in the Macrocoſme, that is, what is his condition, nature, proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, vertue and inclination, what Science, what Art and Induſtry, what Order, what Study, what fortune, what good, and what evill men draw, and handle from him on the earth.</p>
               <p>Whereby it will appear, that <hi>Saturn</hi> is not only without a man in the Major world; but alſo in man, with all the legion and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their adjunct Starrs.</p>
               <p>Then how the whole <hi>Astrologie,</hi> that is, the nature, propriety and operation of this Planet ought to be Theologized, by the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:165235:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Touching the <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> of <hi>Saturn,</hi> of what kind it is, and how it ought to be Theologized.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAturn</hi> as to the deſcription of his ſubſtance and nature in the Macrocoſme, is one of the chief of thoſe ſeven Starrs, which we call <hi>Planets,</hi> or Governours of the world, walking next of all in the aiery Region under the Firmament or Zodiac, and ordained in a certain Sphear, or Circle, or Manſion; the circuit of circle he fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, he paſſeth over once in the ſpace of thirty years time, through the twelve celeſtiall Signs extant in the Zodiac. His body ariſing from the Element of Fire, and illuminating that, is cheriſhing, and governing the earth; and what are in and on the earth; his body is fiery and globous, his Aſtralic force, which is the firmamentall or ſyderean Spirit, is inviſible. Now <hi>Saturn</hi> is conditioned with that nature &amp; propriety from the firſt creation, that he may ſend forth &amp; exerciſe the vertue &amp; operation of his ſplend or &amp; light, in his ſubjects exiſting here and there in the foure Elements, as are vegetables, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, animalls, properly and <hi>in ſpecie</hi> pertaining to him, wherein he effects and frameth ſuch a nature and vertue, as he hath in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Now <hi>Saturn</hi> hath his ſubjects appropriate to himſelf in every kind of creature, amongſt Vegetables he hath his young twigs, his herbs, his plants, his flowers, his trees in which he operates by his influence after his manner: So amongſt mineralls and mettalls, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo amongſt animalls, creeping, going, (creatures,) cattell, beaſts, watery and volatill (creatures.)</p>
               <p>For the whole univerſity of the creatures of this world with us men, is divided into ſeven kinds or aſſemblies, and diſperſed into every region, which anſwer to theſe ſeven Governours in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vertues and proprieties, as well internall as externall.</p>
               <p>But touching the Aſtronomicall condition of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and the reſt of the Planets, to wit, what kind of motion, poſition, courſe, quantity, diſtance, oppoſition, conjunction, and other dimenſions of this kind they have amongſt themſelves; alſo touching the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their weights in mettalls, &amp;c. it is not our purpoſe here to handle them; concerning ſuch kind of things conſult Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall books, and Chimicall books, and the like, publiquely extant abroad; <hi>but we rather handle and ſhew this.</hi> How all the ſtudies, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165235:20"/>offices, and kinds of life of all men have their originall from the Starrs, and to which Planet every thing is to be referred: Then how the whole Aſtrologie ought to be Theologized, that is, how every one of us ought to know, diſcern, hate, put off, ſay aſide, and deny the old man made of Aſtrologie, with all his Wiſdom, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Knowledge, Prudence, Induſtry, Art, and whatſoever a man hath, occupies and poſſeſſeth of the gifts of Nature, and in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of himſelf, and all that he hath, as well within as without, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to grow a child again, to be made an infant, yea a fool; and to put on the new Man which is created according to God, to walk in newneſſe of life, to die to ſin, and to live to juſtice, to know that Babilonian Whore and her Beaſt, &amp;c. and to preſerve himſelf from her, &amp;c. to know the forbidden Tree, and to eat of the Tree of Life, and to paſſe over from nature into grace, to be made a new creature, to be born again, to tranſplant himſelf from the terrene Paradiſe into the Heavenly; to labour ſix daies, and rightly to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the ſeventh, and the like. This is the intention, end and ſcope of this our work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Saturnists, or the worſhippers of Saturn,</hi> whoſe minds, deſires, wills, inclinations, affections, concupiſcences, pleaſures, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, ſpeculations, inventions, actions and labours are aſcribed to <hi>Saturn, as to their study and kind of life,</hi> are men in whom is and flouriſheth all kind of ſcience and induſtry.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cain</hi> was a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman. <hi>Abell</hi> a keeper of ſheep.</note> 
                  <hi>Of all Agriculture,</hi> as are Husbandmen, Countreymen, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Tyllers of the ground: alſo Mowers, Threſhers, Heardsmen, Swineheards, Paſtors of cattell Purveyors of corne, or thoſe which exerciſe merchandiſe with corn and pulſe: alſo dreſſers of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, that purge Wines, Gardners: in brief all agriculture, with all its ſpecies.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jabal</hi> was the father of inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in tents and feeders of ſheep.</note> The whole art and ſcience <hi>edificatory</hi> under; with all kind of Artificers and Workmen, are comprehended, as Rough Maſons, Stonecutters, Carpenters, Joyners, and in brief the whole admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of <hi>oeconomie,</hi> or houſehold affairs joyned with parſimony or frugality.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tuball Cain</hi> found out every ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice of braſſe and iron.</note> The whole art and <hi>Metallic ſcience,</hi> which teacheth the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſearching, and trying the bowells of the earth, and of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging mineralls, metalls, and riches, the provocations of evills: alſo <hi>Treaſurers,</hi> and whoſoever ſeem to ſeek and take their livelyhood from the earth by the labours of their hands, as are Potters, Tile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165235:20"/>bearers of dead bodies, Fiſhmongers, Rootſellers, Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and others of this kind: and alſo Clothiers, Linnenweavers, Shomakers, Coblers, Cardmakers, &amp;c. Alſo ſolitary men, as Monks, Hermits, and like to theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As touching the mind and vices,</hi> Saturniſts are avaritious men, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of gain, uſurers, lenders for gain, Jews, Tolgatherers or Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, tenacious, livers ſparingly, Mammoniſts, altogether watching for their proper commodities: Alſo theeves, robbers, makers of falſe money, Sergeants, falſe Judges, Hangmen, Inchanters, Evill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers: alſo men auſtere by nature, froward, more ſad then joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Thoughtfull, Melancholic, Phantaſtic, very Silent, Tedious, Infidells, Sacrilegious, and what kinds of life ſoever of this ſort. Likewiſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, laborious, full of buſineſſe, tumbling, macera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and wearying themſelves in continuall cares, and furthermore whatſoever appears like to theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As to the quality of the body and externall manners;</hi> Saturniſts are men worn with years and age, as well men as women, covered with gray-hairs, with a ſlender and lean body, thin beard, eyes lying deep in the head, with a neglected form, and not amiable, alwaies looking grimly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, halting, beggers, often ſick, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All theſe ſtudies, and all and ſingular</hi> kinds of life of men, as they are formed and ſeen abroad amongſt all Nations, people, kindreds, &amp;c. of the whole compaſſe of the earth, are referred to the Heaven, Region, Dominion, Nature, and inclination of <hi>Saturn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, all theſe kind of men, with all their ſtudies and kinds of life, as well honeſt as diſhoneſt, as well good as bad, as well private as publique, <hi>are worſhippers of Saturn,</hi> for that in the handling of <hi>Saturn,</hi> that is, in the drawing forth of the nature of the Saturnine light, they ſpend their labour and time, and by diligent ſtudy and inquiſition they draw forth, ſearch, produce and manifeſt thoſe things of <hi>Saturn,</hi> which are in naturall things.</p>
               <p>All the Induſtries, Inventions, Arts, Actions and labours of theſe men in every ſeaſon have proceeded, and as yet do proceed, <hi>from the internall inviſible heaven,</hi> which is in the <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> and are part of the Light of Nature, in which man walketh, whether well or ill, honeſtly or filthily, according to the diverſity of his flexible will and deſire, as well to good as to evill, and men are buſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the externall ſubjects of the Macrocoſme, without which, vain were the vigour, and endeavour of the Light of Nature in man. For
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165235:21"/>every action of the Microcoſme from within, tends to the ſubjects of the Macrocoſme without; becauſe there the works of man are perfected (or performed.) For indeed man hath from the Light of Nature in himſelf, the Science of plowing and tilling the earth, Fields, building houſes, of ſeeking and handling mettalls, &amp;c. but he hath not in himſelf the ſubjects matter and inſtruments, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he takes them from the Macrocoſme, and perfects his work, found out and excogitated, by the Light of Nature. Thus ſeeing all the externall work of men ariſe from within, from the inviſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of the internall Starrs, ever and anon aſcending and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning forth by cogitations and imaginations, and are perfected by externall operations and labours; we may from every work of man ſee and know the conſtitution of the internall heaven, what kind of poſiture, what aſcendents, what motions, conſtellations and inclinations every artificer hath; where it is wonderfull to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the variety of the naturall light. Hence by how much the more the artifice doth appear in externall works, by ſo much the more and more perfect, hath the conſtitution and influence of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall heaven, been with the workman.</p>
               <p>Therefore we muſt know that every ſpecies, of whatſoever Science, Art, &amp; Faculty, is a ſingular conſtellation, ſtarr, inclination &amp; influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aſcending from the inward heaven, and ſhining, acting and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating one by one in man; therefore all the cogitations, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, inventions, deſires, ſtudies and intentions of Saturniſts bent or inclined to good or evill, are the Aſtra's or Starrs aſcending from the inward heaven, &amp; are the operation of the Saturn, of the Microcoſm in the ſoul with his Stars agreeable to himſelf, in which cogitations and operations <hi>that crafty Serpent,</hi> which almoſt none in this our age ſeems to know, is powerfull and raigneth, by leave permitted to him by God, to tempt and prove man (placed in the midſt) by theſe delights of the Light of Nature, and of the things of this world, and to bend the will, love, deſire and concupiſcence thereof from Good to Evill, from God to the Creature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto man (O grievous!) is too too ready and prompt.</p>
               <p>Truly <hi>innumerable</hi> and infinite are the multitude of men living on the earth, which are found in this kind or practiſe of Aſtrologie: For it is (which we would have miſtically ſpoken) one of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Congregations or Generations of the world, or people wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the <hi>Queen of Heaven,</hi> or venerating and worſhipping the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165235:21"/>
                  <hi>Babilonian Whore,</hi> and adoring the Beaſt endowed with ſeven heads and ten horns. And this is the ſence which ſleeps with wiſdom, which will appear better by the following things.</p>
               <p>Now as the <hi>externall heaven</hi> in the Macrocoſme, alwaies and ever and anon is rolled and turned about with a perpetuall motion, and alwaies other and other Starrs are ſeen to appear aſcending, and alwaies deſcending, ſo as there is a perpetuall mutation and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcitude of the actions of Nature labouring in the greater world, where now it is Winter, now Spring, now Summer, now Autumn, now day, now night, now fair weather, now tempeſt, now ſnow, now rain, now winds, now ſtorms, now this, now that, &amp;c. which are all the Aſtralic operations of the Heaven of the Macrocoſme: So alſo in like ſort is the courſe, viciſcitude, motion and revolution of the Starrs, ever and anon aſcending, and deſcending in the heaven or ſoul of the leſſer world, that is, <hi>The ſoul, or our ſyderean Spirit, is an unquiet Spirit,</hi> wherein the aſcendent cogitations, new concupiſcences, various deſires, are alwaies moved, excited and felt, now willing this, now nilling that, now ſo, now thus, now we rejoyce, now we ſorrow, now we are beaten and agitated with theſe, now with thoſe affections, now we are occupied with theſe, now with thoſe buſineſſes and labours, all which are nothing els then the Aſtrologie of the Microcoſme, to be Theologized in all of us that are willing to uſe them piouſly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But how and wherefore ought the Astrologie of</hi> Saturn <hi>to be Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logized in Man?</hi> If thou askeſt me, wherefore and how all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Sciences appertaining to the Aſtrologie of <hi>Saturn,</hi> together with all the kinds of the Saturnine life, ought and may be Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gized? I again ask thee, that thou tell me the cauſe;</p>
               <p>Wherefore, according to that great precept of God, we ought to labour and finiſh our work in ſix daies, but the ſeventh day to ſanctifie the Sabbath: or,</p>
               <p>Wherefore we cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe beatitude in eternall life, unleſſe we ſhall be converted and be made as <hi>infants.</hi> For theſe have one and the ſame reaſon and cauſe, tend to one, will one, belong to one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The anſwer therefore is:</hi> therefore we ought to Theologize A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, therefore we ought to labour ſix daies, and ſanctifie the ſeventh: therefore we ought to be converted and become as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, becauſe nothing at all but the <hi>New Creature,</hi> the new Man
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:165235:22"/>from Heaven, he that is regenerate from above, he that is born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of immortall ſeed, is required to the poſſeſſion or acquiſition of the Kingdom of Heaven, not the old Man from the Earth ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king earthly things, gaping after earthly things, rejoycing in earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things occupied, delighted in earthly things, loving, poſſeſſing, ſavouring earthly things: I ſay not ſuch, but as we have now ſaid, the man born again from above, ſeeking thoſe things which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and not thoſe things which are below, not ariſing from the will of the fleſh, and not of the will of man, but of God.</p>
               <p>But to the end that we may be the better underſtood of the ruder ſort, firſt we will handle a few things in generall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Theologization of Aſtrologie?</hi> afterwards we will ſet upon our <hi>Saturn,</hi> with his profeſſions and faculties, where we ſhall demonſtrate to the eye, <hi>That in the ſole Theologization of Aſtrologie is to be ſought and found the gate of Paradiſe, to eat of the tree or word of life, which is in the midſt of Paradiſe, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo what is that ſtrait gate that leads to life, which few find; and that the broad way, which leads to hell which many walk; Alſo, <hi>what is that Babiloniſh Whore,</hi> with whom all the people of the world commit fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. and many, and thoſe the greateſt Theologicall miſteries are here ſhewn to the intelligent, which otherwiſe are and abide hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from the eyes of all mortalls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore to Theologize Astrologie,</hi> is nothing els then to labour ſix daies, and to ſanctifie the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> that is to reſt and deſiſt from labour, and to keep holy day in God, with the ſpirit, ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. VVhich God the Father ſeriouſly commanded to his people, by the Law <hi>in the old Teſtament in theſe words,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Remember the Sabbath day that ye may ſanctifie it, ſix daies ſhalt thou labour, and do all thy work; but the ſeventh day ſhall be a Sabbath to the Lord thy God: thou ſhalt not do any work, neither thou, nor thy ſon, nor thy daughter, nor thy ſervant, nor thy maid, nor thy beast, nor the ſtranger which is in thy gates: for in ſix daies the Lord made heaven and earth, the Sea and whatſoever is in them, and reſted the ſeventh day: therefore the Lord bleſſed the Sabbath day and ſanctified it, Alſo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in ſix daies thou ſhalt do thy works, but the ſeventh day thou ſhalt rest; that thy Oxe and thy Aſſe may reſt together, and the ſon of thy hand maid, and the ſtranger may be refreſhed</hi> (or take breath.) <hi>And in all that I have ſaid to you, you ſhall be wary,</hi> to wit, becauſe of the Serpent.<note place="margin">Dent. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Alſo obſerve the Sabbath day, that ye may
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:165235:22"/>ſanctifie it: even as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee: ſix daies ſhalt thou labour and do all thy work, but on the ſeventh day ſhall be the Sabbath of the Lord thy God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But although the divine Commandement amongſt the vulgar hath ſeemed, and yet doth ſeem to be ſpoken, only touching the corporall and externall labour and reſt for reparing the ſtrength of the body: yet thoſe to whom it is given (as well amongſt the Jews as Chriſtians) to know and underſtand the miſteries of the mind of God, and of his Kingdome, they I ſay, have known a far more profound and better cauſe and reaſon of this precept, of ſanctifying the Sabbath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the new Teſtament to Theologize Aſtrologie</hi> is according to the doctrine of Chriſt and the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>To receive the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> as a child or infant, to be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from above, having renounced and left all things to deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſeek the Kingdom of God, which lyeth hidden in us as a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in a field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The labours of the ſix daies</hi> are all the actions, operations, ſtudies, offices, buſineſſes and occupations of all men in the whole earth, and in all Iſlands, and in every Sea amongſt all orders, ſtates and kinds of life, whatſoever all men every where, every time act, ſtudy, handle, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, this they do by the Light of Nature, according to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Sciences. Now the ſeventh part of thoſe labours, ſtudies and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men are referred unto <hi>Saturn,</hi> the ſeverall kinds whereof we have before recited.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moreover the ſanctification of the Sabbath,</hi> divinely ordained and commanded to man on the ſeventh day, is, to ceaſe once in a week from all labour and handling of naturall things, and actuall ſtudies, to deſiſt from the Aſtrologicall life, that is, to lay aſide every motion and action, as well of the mind, as of the body, by an abſolute abnegation and oblivion of the whole creature and of himſelf, as well within as without, <hi>to give and offer himſelf wholly to God,</hi> with all that we are, within the ſix daies we have known, ſtudied, gotten and gained by our labors, as well in the internall gifts of wiſdom, as in the getting of externall things. Hither, hither and to this Centre tends that divine Commandement, touching the ſanctifying of the Sabbath, as by the following things will moſt pleaſantly be laid open.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> A ſpecificall Declaration, how the Astrologie of <hi>Saturn</hi> in Man ought and may be Theologized.</head>
               <p>FOr as much as hitherto we have heard, that all the ſciences, actions, ſtudies, &amp; ſtates of life of all men, by a certain inevitable neceſſity
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165235:23"/>ought to be Theologized, or by the exerciſe, or ſanctification of the mental Sabbath be laid aſide, denyed, put off &amp; accounted for nothing: now we would particularly ſee, how the Aſtrologic of <hi>Saturn</hi> is to be Theologized in us. For becauſe infinite is the multitude of men, only handling and exerciſing this Saturnine Aſtrologie. And we do ſet down firſt of all in a certain Paradoxicall ſence, that is above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intellect of the Vulgar: <hi>That no husbandman, Countryman, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Gardner, Herbeſeller, Vinedreſſer, Steward, Builder, Mettleman, Potter, Weaver, Cobler, Shomaker,</hi> &amp;c. can ever enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, or come to the poſſeſſion of a heavenly life, unleſſe he learn to drive away, to ſubject this power, his Saturnine Heaven, with all his aſcendent Starrs, and reſiſt every inclination thereof, tending to evil, through the inſtinct of the Serpent, raign over it, &amp; overcome it.</p>
               <p>Good God, here will ſome ignorant ſay from the inſtinct of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> of what kind is this your Theologization of Aſtrologie, which you here handle? what mortal can believe, that a husbandman, a farmer, a ſteward, a vinedreſſer, a potter, a mettleman, a mechanick, a carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c. cannot be made an heir &amp; poſſeſſor of the Kingdom of heaven.</p>
               <p>What is the Light of Nature, to be contemned and altogether reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and muſt we ceaſe from all labour? what ought we not at all to act, work, ſtudy, learn, ſearch, but to be plainly idle? whence ſhall we receive food and rayment, and other neceſſaries, to the ſuſtentation of life; ſeeing no man whoſoever is buſied in the ſtudies, labours, and works aboveſaid, can from them attain to eternall ſalvation? the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this book ſeems to be wonderfull indeed and eſtranged from truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I anſwer,</hi> theſe things do not ſeem ſtrange or obſcure but to the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, nor are they indeed a hairs breadth eſtranged from truth, ſo that they be rightly received and underſtood. For nothing can be ſo truly ſpoken or written, that by the ruder and leſſe intelligent may not be called into doubt, or be eſteemed even for a lie.</p>
               <p>But a leſſon read (which) pleaſeth, being repeated ten times it will pleaſe. <hi>Loe this our ſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou art a Husbandman, a Countryman, a Farmer, a Steward, a Gardner, a Seller of herbs, a Vinedreſſer, a Potter, a Mettleman, a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter, a Builder, &amp;c. or buſied in ſome other like kind of life, then thou art conſtituted and walkeſt in the <hi>ſphere of Saturn,</hi> and art go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the Saturnine Starrs (which are in thee) ever and anon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending in thy imagination, cogitation, and ſences, ruling thee, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thee hither and thither, even as thy pleaſure draweth thee by free will, and the inward ſerpent perſwadeth thee.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:165235:23"/>
               <p>Now unleſſe thou as a wiſe man ſhalt be cautious and attent, and ſhalt over-rule thy Starrs running up and down, flouriſhing and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating in thee, or ſhalt Theologize thy Aſtrologie, that is, unleſſe thou ſhalt learn to Sabbathize, and to ceaſe from all thy work, and keep holy the Lords day, according to the mind and ſence of the divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept; it altogether is and abides impoſſible to thee, by any means to enter into the Kingdom of God, and come to the poſſeſſion of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſalvation: For I will make it clear by a moſt manifeſt demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That never any Husbandman, Farmer, Countryman, Steward, Mettleman, &amp;c. could enter into the Kingdom of God, who neglecting and omitting the ſanctification of the Sabbath departed out of this world. But I would thou ſhouldeſt take theſe things rightly.</p>
               <p>My judgment is <hi>that no Saturniſt,</hi> ſuch as are before recited, can enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but that he ought to be throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and be made as an infant; then at length he is fit to take, enter and poſſeſſe the Kingdom of God, not indeed as a Husbandman, a Farmer, a Steward, a Builder, a Vinedreſſer, a Seller of herbs, a Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, a Potter, &amp;c. becauſe there is no ſuch thing to be done there for ſuch workmen; but ſee thou be as a child, and infant, as a new Creature, as the Son of God. For no man hath aſcended to heaven, but he which deſcended from heaven, <hi>the ſon of God which is Chriſt,</hi> and as many as received him, he gave them power to be made the ſons of God: Now to receive Chriſt requires an inevitable putting off &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, yea deſtruction of the old Creature, of the old man created of earth, and the new birth of the ſame from above, from whence alſo Chriſt is ariſen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore the reaſons and cauſes,</hi> for which the Husbandman, the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the Steward, the Builder, the Vinedreſſer, the Mettleman, the Potter, the Weaver, &amp;c. cannot come into heaven, are theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe in the celeſtiall Paradiſe, or the Country of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, there are no grounds, nor oxen, nor plows for Husbandmen, nor farms or Lands for Farmers, nor houſes nor granaries for Stewards, nor ſtones nor wood for Builders, nor vineyards nor forks for Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers, nor gardens, herbs, plants, ſeeds for Herbſellers, nor moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains fertill in metalls for Mettlemen, nor loam, nor clay for Potters, nor flax nor wooll for Weavers, and therefore there is not any need of any Husbandman, Steward, Builder; Mettleman, Potter, Weaver, neither ſhall thoſe which inhabit there, want ſuch kind of ſcience and induſtry. For all theſe things are, and are only to be found under the Zodiac in this corruptible world, where in the laſt day at one time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and at once, they ſhall be taken away and ceaſe with the world.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165235:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:165235:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:165235:25"/>
               <p>So far therefore my husbandman as thy field, thy oxe, and thy plow, ſhall be tranſported after the laſt day to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: So far alſo ſhalt thou thy ſelf with thy ruſtickſcience and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, after this life enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, that is never. Therefore put off the old earthly and naturall man, with all his ſcience, prudence, craftineſſe, which thou uſeſt in the handling of natural things, and put on the new man which alone ſavours and deſires hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things, and leadeth thee to heavenly things, by the exerciſe of the true Sabbath, to be had in the ſpirit of thy mind every week.</p>
               <p>And ſo far my Vinedreſſer as thy Vine, and thy fork ſhall be found after the laſt day, in the Kingdom of Heaven: ſo far alſo ſhalt thou appear there with thy vinitory ſcience and induſtry, that is never. For then all old things are paſſed away.</p>
               <p>And ſo far my ſteward as thy houſhold-ſtuffe and granaties, ſhall be found out in the Kingdom of Heaven, after the world is blotted out: ſo far alſo ſhalt thou thy ſelf be there with thy ſcience and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of domeſtick parſimony, that is never. For we do not act thoſe things there, which we are wont here.</p>
               <p>And ſo far as my Gardner, my Potter, &amp;c. thy colworts, herbs, plants, trees, with thy garden, and thy loam and clay ſhall after the world is defaced, remain, and be transferred into the perpetuall hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo far alſo ſhalt thou thy ſelf with all thy plantatory and pot-making ſcience, be promoted to the heavenly manſion, that is never. For the ſubjects and matter being wanting, what can thy ſcience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thee?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So alſo</hi> it is with all the reſt of the kinds, and Sciences, and Arts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Aſtrologie of <hi>Saturn,</hi> as are, Mettlemen, Rough Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Stonecutters, Smith and Carpenters, all kind of Mechanicks, Colliers, Cornſellers, Mowers, Heardsmen, Clothiers, Weavers, Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, Coblers, and the like.</p>
               <p>All theſe have their matter and ſubjects about which they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant, and with which they are occupied without them in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſm, which being taken away &amp; withdrawn, all things wil be taken away &amp; withdrawn with them: &amp; they have within themſelves in their ſoul, in which the light of Nature, the wiſdom, induſtry, art, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding rightly to inſtute, handle &amp; perform their works, which ſoul, and which light are nothing els, then the Aſtralic Heaven and Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Microcoſm, where every ſcience, art &amp; work, hath his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſtarr with the aſcendants convenient to it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Therefore this ſcience and operation is once a week to be laid aſide and put off: and we muſt ſabathize in God, that God may act and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:165235:25"/>his work in us, to wit, the work of our converſion, repentance, amendment, newbirth, and of the new Creation, that we may be made fit to enter into his Kingdom after death and the reſurrection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Furthermore,</hi> alſo for this cauſe none of the aforeſaid can ſee, enter, poſſeſſe the Kingdom of Heaven; becauſe ſuch a workman is only born of fleſh and blood: is the old Creature of the earth of this world, and is the ſon of the Firmament, the off-ſpring of Nature; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he excells in the knowledge of naturall things: yet all his ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and knowledge is to take an end with the life of time. He that would be capable of heaven, ought to be the new Man born again of God, regenerate, the new Creature. For nothing that is earthly can take or poſſeſſe heaven: therefore none of thoſe which we have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto recited, and ſhall recite in the following things ſhall come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſſe ye be converted and become as an infant, who knows none of theſe things. There ſhall be a new Heaven and a new earth, old things are paſſed away, ſaith he which doth it, all things are made new. A new heaven therefore requires new inhabitants, fit for it, and capable of it, for as man at firſt was created of the old heaven, and of the old earth, and was born of mortall ſeed, in which earth he now temporally dwelleth: So it alſo behoveth him to be created of that new heaven, and of that new birth, and to be born again, to be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated of the immortall ſeed, in which earth he would be and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit eternally.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third reaſon is,</hi> becauſe the Light of Nature, with all kinds of their Sciences is given to man, for this life only to till the earth, for the labour of his hands, to eat his bread in the ſweat of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp;c. and belongs only to the ſuſtentation of the naturall and temporall life, living in the mortall body, and the body being dead, and the world blotted out, no ſuch thing remaineth, therefore we have no need of corn, vines, buildings, tents, houſes, garments, meat, &amp;c. therefore neither knowledge nor deſire of getting or labouring for ſuch things, the cauſe ceaſing, the effect ceaſeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fourth reaſon is,</hi> becauſe man was not made of God finally for this world, or for thoſe things which are in this world: but chiefly for the Kingdom of God, where none of theſe things is found or is in uſe, which in this life are every where agitated and handled with men, throughout the divers ſhops of the light of Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fifth is,</hi> becauſe man was therefore conſtituted for a time only in this world, that he might aſcend from the inferiour things, and ſeek after the ſuperiour things, that is, that by naturall light and wiſdome, as it were from a looking glaſſe or ſhadow, he might learn to know
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:165235:26"/>and apprehend the heavenly light and wiſdom, at whoſe Majeſty and Glory, all naturall things, although glorious, might plainly vaniſh and be annihilated; and ſo leaving the inferiour and leſſer light, he ſhould ſuddenly betake himſelf to, and follow the greater and ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our light, and departing from this tranſitory world, forſaking and accompting all things for nothing, which he receiveth, hath and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in this time from the world, and having denied himſelf as a naked and new-born infant, depart into that eternall manſion, and region of the eternall Country, and ſo come thither faſting and empty from the poſſeſſion of all naturall ſcience, as if he had never at all been in this world, or had not known any the leaſt ſtate of this world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But theſe things are not propounded and written to that end,</hi> that they ſhould happen in contempt of Philoſophy, or of naturall ſciences, arts and faculties, which are and flouriſh amongſt men, and which in this life cannot but be, but rather that we being fraught with the ſagacity of the Light of Nature, may be led further, may go forward and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to the knowledge of the greater light, which may confer upon us a new birth, eternall life and ſalvation. For to all that covet and deſire the Kingdom of God, is the old man made of nature to be put off, and laid down; yea to be buried in an abſolute abnegation and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, as well of himſelf as of all thoſe things which he hath, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſtudieth, knoweth, learneth; and the new Man is to be put on, which is created according to God, where there is neither Jew nor Greek, neither male nor female, neither bond nor free, but the new Creature.</p>
               <p>I ſay, the new Creature is required to poſſeſſe the Kingdom of God, wherein there is nothing left of the old leven. The old leven is the knowledge of good and evill, beginning to ſpring in man from the forbidden tree, and is the prudence or ſubtilty of the ſerpent: But the new heaven is the heavenly wiſdom, the ſimplicity of the dove, from whom alone true life and beatitude flowes, and which alſo only ſhall bear rule in the elect heirs of the Kingdom of God, the naturall and terrene wiſdom, being then utterly together and at once ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up, blotted out and extinct.</p>
               <p>For the Kingdom of God is of ſuch only, who are converted from the old Creature into the new, and become as children, who never knew neither good nor evill. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>John</hi> 3.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>PAge 5. line 22. read <hi>ſome.</hi> p. 6. l. 25. (and in divers other places) for Arthens, r. <hi>Archcus.</hi> p. 20. l. 11. r l <hi>was</hi> formed <hi>as.</hi> p. 22. l. 31. r. <hi>premiſe.</hi> p. 25. l. 10. r. <hi>creatures.</hi> p. 30. l. 25. r. <hi>cure.</hi> l. 26. r. <hi>brings.</hi> p. 40. l. 15. r. <hi>wood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprimatur. <hi>Theodore Jennings.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
